<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1251" ?>
<string_table>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_0"><text>I don't know. Feels like I need it, but my gut says I shouldn't.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_1"><text>I don't know. This isn't my first day in the Zone, and taking something like that right away is risky.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_2"><text>Push that on some green rookie. I'm not convinced yet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_3"><text>The Zone's too dangerous a place to grab just anything. I need to think.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_4"><text>Pal, this isn't my first year in the Zone... I'm not taking it for now. Maybe later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_5"><text>Build yourself a reputation first. Buying from you just like that feels shady.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_6"><text>I can see everyone's hustling however they can. I don't need it right now. Feels shady.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_7"><text>I don't know. Feels like I need it, but my gut says I shouldn't.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_8"><text>I'd take it, but something about it feels off.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_9"><text>I'll pass for now. You never know.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_10"><text>Not taking it for now. My own stuff is more reliable.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_11"><text>We're supplied as it is. Is it even worth it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_12"><text>You should try it on yourself first. Who knows. I'll pass for now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_13"><text>We're already supplied. Unless it's dirt cheap...</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_14"><text>We've got our own. I'd need to think about it. Depends on the price.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_15"><text>We have our own supply lines, but I'll think about your offer.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_16"><text>Cool it, pal, we've got enough of our own. Come back later, we'll talk.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_17"><text>This is Duty. We've got almost everything here. Come back later, we'll see.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_18"><text>We're fully supplied. Extra stock never hurts, of course. Come back later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_19"><text>Wouldn't be bad to have in reserve. I'm not taking it right now. I'll think on it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_20"><text>We're supplied. Maybe we'll take yours too, but not right now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_21"><text>If you'd offered some weed, that'd be different. Come back later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_22"><text>Better dump that expired crap on Duty. Feels shady.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_23"><text>I'll think about it, but bring something to clear the head while you're at it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_24"><text>If we can agree on the price, I might take it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_25"><text>Started doing business, have you? Good for you, but I'm not buying just yet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_26"><text>You should've offered some weed instead. Though this wouldn't hurt either, of course. I'll think about it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_27"><text>This is Freedom. Everything's sold freely here, if we can agree on the price...</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_28"><text>You're late, we're already buzzing.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_29"><text>You should've offered vodka, but your stuff might do for a morning fix.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_30"><text>Bring vodka next time. Though this won't hurt either.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_31"><text>All right, pal, lay out the whole lot. Maybe then we'll talk.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_32"><text>Don't try to sell me garbage. Give me a real price, then we'll talk.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_33"><text>I thought you'd offer something for a buzz. I'll think about it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_34"><text>Pal, a little later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_35"><text>Don't bust my brains. I don't need it right now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_36"><text>We've already got pills. If yours are better, we'll talk.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_37"><text>Your business doesn't fly here. Drop the price, then we'll talk.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_38"><text>Pal, a little later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_39"><text>Don't bust my brains. I don't need it right now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_40"><text>No... why would I? I use traditional remedies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_41"><text>Why would I need it? Ignat can get proper remedies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_42"><text>Offer that to stalkers over there. We use our own.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_43"><text>We don't need it, thanks...</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_44"><text>I've got our own hunters' remedies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_45"><text>No thanks, nothing beats our own remedies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_46"><text>Just between us girls, your medicine is crap.</text></string>
<string id="dm_exchange_info_47"><text>Why would I need it? Ignat can get proper remedies.</text></string>

<string id="dm_chang_pda_info_0"><text>I don't know. Feels like I need it, but my gut says I shouldn't.</text></string>
<string id="dm_chang_pda_info_1"><text>I don't know. This isn't my first day in the Zone, and taking something like that right away is risky.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_0"><text>I've heard of those, and I'd rather not have. Once one of those trucks rolled into a town, and afterward everybody there died out, every last one. Now they call that place the Dead City. That's how it is. Another truck was seen somewhere near the Red Forest, and after that people started disappearing there. Whoever goes there never comes back...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_1"><text>Those trucks are omens of trouble... If you ever see one, take it as the first bell ringing, and the last one too. That's the Zone telling you you'll be riding in one of those trucks soon enough... Thank God I haven't seen a single one yet. You have, have you? Then that's it, you're done for, and I'm not talking about this anymore.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_2"><text>Get lost with your trucks! Somebody else asked around about them too, and where is he now? See that cross over there? Go say hello. You'll be there soon enough if questions like that interest you, and then you can ask him... No, don't even ask me.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_3"><text>People say all kinds of things. Mostly nonsense. Stalkers are superstitious, everybody has their own hang-ups. And this topic's taboo for everyone, nobody likes talking about it. It's nonsense, sure... though who knows. There must be something to it. Rumors don't spring up out of nowhere. So I'd better keep my mouth shut too. You never know...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_4"><text>"Death trucks," you mean? Knock on wood... God forbid I ever meet one. They say it's worse than the Black Mark: see one once, and you're bound to end up in one. I don't even want to talk about them...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_5"><text>The ones with corpses in them? That's some question... Like there aren't any better topics. Don't mention them again. That's like talking about the Grim Reaper dropping by for you today... I don't even want to think about it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_6"><text>I've heard about them in passing, but the men don't like talking about them. There's something terrifying about them. Someone even said they haul half-dead zombies around the Zone. Zombies behind the wheel too. It picks a spot, dumps them in a heap, and then they crawl all over the place like roaches... Filthy business...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_7"><text>What? I wouldn't wish meeting one of those trucks on my worst enemy. Anyone who sees one gets this stubborn urge to come back and "take a ride" in it. Like some kind of pull. And what it carries is corpses. So if you spot one from a distance, give it a wide berth.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_8"><text>You mean the corpse wagons? Someone said they're self-propelled, like radio-controlled. Like the scientists came up with that shit so they wouldn't have to run around the Zone themselves... always studying something... nerds. One guy even said they recruit volunteers and take them for a ride in that truck, but nobody survives the trip... All they care about is studying things, for fuck's sake! People die because of their research and they couldn't care less.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_9"><text>I heard the scientists have teamed up with the military and are running experiments like that. They load up corpses and zombies, then drive them around the Zone. After each corpse they cut it into pieces and study how the Zone affected it... And if they don't have enough for their report, they shoot stalkers or zombify them to fill the truck. Watch yourself around the scientists... they could shove anybody into that truck.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_10"><text>There's a rumor somebody collects organs that way, then smuggles them outside the Zone. They load up fresh corpses, still warm, and spirit them away. Former stalkers do the loading, the kind that don't give a damn about anything anymore as long as there's money in it... Fuckers! And if you stumble across them during one of those harvests, they'll plug you without a second thought and load you up too. For cash they'd kill their own mother, the bastards!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_11"><text>People saw a truck like that once. Weird mystical shit. It came from God knows where and God knows how. Rolled in, stopped... and silence. Then it vanished just as mysteriously. But the strangest part was that there was nobody at the wheel... Or maybe there was, only invisible, like a ghost or something. And in the back, probably the souls of those killed in the Zone too... Gives me gooseflesh just thinking about it...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_cars_info_12"><text>They say one of them drove through here. Nobody really knows where from, but the men say it's a sign. Means it's time to get out. It's a "death truck." You get the meaning? DEATH. Only it was empty. And why was it empty? Because it came here looking to stock up on corpses... It's no good, not good at all...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_13"><text>Strange little trucks. They don't even look real... Just another incomprehensible thing, like everything else in this Zone. My advice is don't go near them. They're like anomalies, another spawn of the Zone. I can't even imagine what they are... I only know that anything you can't make sense of in the Zone is best avoided if you want to stay alive.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_14"><text>There's a strange link with them. One of those trucks shows up, then disappears... Seems like nothing, but at the same time reports of stalkers dying start pouring in. I'm sure there's some connection. Like it takes the number of deaths it needs and disappears somewhere... along with those poor bastards. That's how it is. God forbid one of them shows up here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_15"><text>Ever heard of Семецкий [TERM?]? They say he used to be a driver, and now he rides around the Zone in one of those trucks. He appears in that truck out of nowhere, then disappears into nowhere. And when word comes in that Семецкий [TERM?] has died, it means one of those trucks vanished somewhere. That's supposed to mean good luck, that you can head out and won't run into a "death truck." Probably nonsense... What's Семецкий [TERM?] got to do with it anyway?..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_16"><text>Those aren't trucks at all. They're alien transport. That's one theory. They came from space and they're studying us. They just disguise themselves that way so they don't spook us, their test subjects. Though that only makes them scarier... They'd be better off flying around in saucers, at least then it'd be clearer who they are and what they want.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_17"><text>It's all nonsense and stalker tall tales. "Death truck"... Nice name, I'll give them that. One guy spun some bullshit and everybody keeps repeating it and trembling: "God forbid, God forbid"... You're just another one who bought those stories about the trucks. It's all bullshit.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_18"><text>Another one. It's a joke, don't you get it? "A little boy climbed into the cab..." Or however it goes... Anyway, "It started up soft, rolled away soft, and a rookie stalker found a hundred corpses." Something like that. Long story short, it's just a gag. Don't take it to heart. Sit down, have a drink, grab a bite, relax.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_19"><text>Everybody says "death truck." But they aren't omens of approaching death, they are death itself. The Zone is God's punishment for everything people have done. And the truck is His message, in a form a man can understand, that death has come and it is inevitable... If you see a truck, don't waste time on foolishness. Pray, and accept what He has in store for you with a light heart.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_20"><text>Those aren't ordinary trucks, they're hearses. And they don't foretell anything, no matter what people say here. If you saw a hearse in an ordinary city, would you think right away, "It's come for me"? Calm down. It's taking someone to be buried, not you. And these trucks have just as little to do with you. It came, it went... what's it to you?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_21"><text>There's no point trying to understand something that's unknowable by nature. Nobody understands what an anomaly is, how it appears, how it disappears. Nobody knows where artifacts come from... These trucks are the same kind of thing. Nobody knows anything and nobody ever will. All that'll keep going around are tales and horror stories about them. What else is left, if there's no way to make sense of it? All people can do is make up stories.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_22"><text>Back when it all first blew, the army and the administration hired truck drivers to haul out the bodies. A sea of people died back then. They hauled them out of Припять [TERM?], out of Лиманск [TERM?], gathered them from the villages. There weren't any anomalies yet, so they tried to pull people out, if only so they could be buried properly, and all that... That's why the drivers themselves started calling their vehicles corpse wagons. But that was a long time ago... and people are still talking.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_23"><text>Who the hell knows. They say there are vehicles hauling stiffs straight through anomalies. I haven't seen it myself, just heard stories. This is the Zone, buddy. You could see flying mammoths racing crocodiles here...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_24"><text>Ah, to hell with them. They say death trains roll along the broken rails over at Янов [TERM?], and you're asking me about trucks... Ask me about airplanes while you're at it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_25"><text>What trucks? You hardly ever walk upright here, you spend most of your time conquering space on your belly...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_26"><text>I'll tell you this: don't stick your nose into questions that aren't yours. The fact you're asking means you aren't afraid, because you don't know anything. I know a little, and I'm afraid. So let's drop it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_27"><text>It's all too strange. They say those things always roam at night. Nobody's seen or heard them by day, but nights are different. It's like the Flying Dutchman: nothing but dead men in those machines, or so I've heard...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_28"><text>Is anything here known for certain at all? Even the scientists don't know, and you're asking me. Ask those nerds sometimes and whatever you bring up, all you get is "blah blah blah" and a long runaround, and in the end their answers are worth nothing. Freeloaders.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_29"><text>That's how they haul the nosiest stalkers out of the Zone. Once the truck bed's full, off they go! Want to join them too?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_30"><text>People say all sorts of things. A rumor came through not long ago that there really are trucks like that. Someone from one of them is even living on the Cordon. Go ask around there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cars_info_31"><text>I think those trucks are basically garbage trucks. Somebody in the center is making or producing something, and they haul all the trash away. Sometimes they carry crates, there are enough of those all over the Zone, sometimes zombies, which are trash too, used-up material... Where else would all this come from?</text></string>

<string id="dm_prizrak_info_0"><text>What Ghost? We run into dead men getting back up around here, and you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_1"><text>Ghost? Nah... I don't remember anyone like that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_2"><text>What Ghost? Believe fewer tall tales... I don't know anything.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_3"><text>Who? A real ghost? And you believe that? Bullshit... Though in the Zone, you can run into just about anything.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_4"><text>People said something about him, I just don't remember who... I think they were talking about him in the Bar. Can't recall.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_5"><text>Ghost? Our boys knew him, they even drank together. Bandits killed him. Or no... I'm mixing him up, that was Фантом [TERM?]. I don't know Ghost.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_6"><text>I've heard of him, but nothing specific. He was here once, but he didn't show off, didn't put himself on display, and generally tried to stay in the shadows and go unnoticed. A ghost, in a word.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_7"><text>Yeah, yeah... funny you should mention him now. I keep thinking who you remind me of... You look a bit like him. Or maybe not him, maybe his companion... It was a long time ago, hard to remember now, and nobody's talked about Ghost himself in ages. I don't really know anything, where he is, what he's up to... But you do resemble him somehow.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_8"><text>Ghost was here once, though it was a long time ago. And he wasn't alone, he had some oddball with him. They kept asking about some kind of metal contraptions. We don't know anything about that stuff, so nobody remembered much. They hung around here a little while, then slipped off somewhere.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_9"><text>Somebody told me he came with some medic, or a doctor. They were looking for medicine or something like that... Seems somebody got caught in an anomaly... I don't know myself, I'm just repeating what I heard.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_10"><text>How could I not know Ghost? Me and the other stalkers talked with him, just like I'm talking with you now. Sure, we were drinking then, but not so much that I'd forget. Most of the talking was between us, though... heh-heh. He was the quiet type, just nodding along to everything. Then he disappeared somewhere. But we had other things on our minds by then. Haven't seen him since.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_11"><text>Ghost? He's one of the founders of the stalker trade. A stalker patriarch, if you can call him that. For a while people kept saying he'd walked almost the whole Zone. Just like they said about Strelok. Maybe they're even the same man. But nobody talks about him anymore. Guess people talked it to death, or everybody got tired of hearing about some legendary stalker.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_12"><text>People said Ghost walked the Zone with Strelok... or maybe still does. It's just that people haven't been saying much about them lately. There was a time when everybody thought it was their duty to tell some story about how they'd practically walked to the center of the Zone with Ghost and Strelok. Lies, of course. I can't even remember what those stories were about now, but back then they were interesting to listen to. What else were you supposed to do with no radio and no TV?</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_13"><text>They say there is no Ghost, that it's all just stories. But there are people like that, the kind who know everything, can do everything, have some business of their own that only they understand, and stay so unnoticed that nobody even believes they're real. Like ghosts, they come and go. I'm telling you, there is a stalker called Ghost. I just don't know where to look for him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_14"><text>They saw him in the Bar once. I didn't see him myself, but they said the whole place suddenly started whispering, "Oh! Ghost! Ghost!" And everyone tried to come up to him on one excuse or another: "Got a smoke?", "Know what time it is?", "Could you tell me how to get to the library?" Everybody practically wanted to touch a living Ghost. That's how it was. Then he hung around a bit and left. I was too late, I'd already missed him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_15"><text>We were sitting by the campfire once when a stalker-looking fellow walked up. He sat down and started talking to one of our guys. I think they knew each other. They kept muttering and muttering. Most of our lot weren't paying much attention, but I heard the name Ghost. Big name, so I started listening, and I didn't understand a damn thing. They kept talking about some kind of generator. Maybe they needed a gas generator or something? And what does Ghost have to do with that? Then they got up, walked off somewhere, and that was it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_16"><text>The name's well known. But I can't tell you anything specific. Ghost wouldn't be Ghost if everybody knew where his hideout was and how to find him. That's why he's Ghost: nobody knows anything concrete about him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_17"><text>Ghost... Strelok... that's all anybody ever talks about, like the rest of the stalkers are somehow worse. No, see, Ghost's a stalker! And me or you, we're nothing. Not worth spit. I don't even want to talk about him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_18"><text>Seems Ghost had dealings with the scientists. Either he worked for them, or he was one of them. Ask them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_19"><text>I heard the military were looking for him. Somebody said the army ran a whole operation in the Zone, hunting some ghosts or shapeshifters. And they were looking for this Ghost too, seeing as his name stands out so much. Maybe they found him, maybe he went to ground somewhere, since nobody says anything about him anymore.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_20"><text>A lot of people say Ghost is a stalker sent by God. Nonsense. He's an ordinary man. He just got lucky and found something very unusual. Most people don't. That's normal. Stalking's like a lottery, there can't be many winners. Ghost just happens to be one of the lucky ones.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_21"><text>Ghost? Nah... I don't remember anyone like that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_22"><text>What Ghost? I don't know anybody with a nickname like that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_23"><text>People said something about him, I just don't remember who... I think they were talking about him. Can't recall.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_24"><text>I heard something about Ghost. Just idle chatter. All I know is he wasn't exactly close with our crowd...</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_25"><text>One man's looking for Ghost, another one's after Strelok... What is this, an information desk?</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_26"><text>Get lost! Go ask the passport office... Heh!</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_27"><text>Somebody was already looking for him. Why do you keep asking around here? None of our boys goes by that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_28"><text>It's a striking name... "Ghost" really has a nice ring to it. Must be one hell of a man to have a nickname like that. But I don't know him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_29"><text>Why are you on my ass? There are people all over the Zone. Today one proudly calls himself Орёл [TERM?], tomorrow he's Пыжик [TERM?]... Yesterday he was Ghost, today he's Ghoul... Go find him.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_30"><text>Hell if I know. Maybe we crossed paths sometime. How are you supposed to remember everyone?</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_31"><text>Did he do something to you, for you to be asking around? You know Телега Сопливый [TERM?]? I do. But on the PDA he shows up as Олег Бритва [TERM?], there you go. So how does your Ghost show up, do you know? Exactly...</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_32"><text>I know him! We were drinking last week, my head's still splitting. Hell if I know where he is now. No... wait, that one wasn't called Ghost, was he? Damn, I'm an idiot... I can't remember anymore.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_33"><text>Think I saw a stalker like that at Agroprom recently. Look around there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_34"><text>We were hanging around here the other day. I don't remember who said it exactly, but there was talk that some guys came back from beyond Барьер [TERM?] with artifacts so good each of them flew home in his own helicopter. Лёха Лысый [TERM?], Дюха Призрак [TERM?], and Витёк Снайпер [TERM?]. They're probably kicking back somewhere in Мальдивы [TERM?] now... Ghost too, I guess.</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_35"><text>Haven't seen him myself, but I heard about one like that. Him and Ремень [TERM?] sold a live Pseudogiant to the scientists. Made a fortune. Probably bullshit, though. Try catching one alive yourself...</text></string>
<string id="dm_prizrak_info_36"><text>Hell if I know which one you're asking about. Андрюха Призрак [TERM?] used to hang around somewhere in Garbage. Серёга Призрак [TERM?] was skulking around Росток [TERM?], and Мишка Призрак [TERM?] wanders around Yantar. Which one do you need?</text></string>

<string id="dm_jokes_info_0"><text>A stalker walks into the Bar with an ostrich and a wet cat. Everyone's surprised, but says nothing. He orders a bottle of vodka, drinks it straight from the neck, and heads for the dark far end of the bar. He sits there and cries. The Barkeep comes over and asks what's wrong.\n- You see, I was at the CNPP, climbed into the sarcophagus, and found a wish granter in there.\nLooks like I'd gone completely crazy without female company, because I wished there would always be a chick with long legs and a wet pussy right beside me.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_1"><text>Two down-on-their-luck thugs are sitting by the campfire, dreaming:\n
- Ah, fuck, if only we could hobble all the way to the Monolith. Then I'd really make it big! Hell, I'd wish for... five grand in rubles!\n
Pause. His companion asks in confusion:\n
- Listen, pal, maybe... six grand, huh?\n
Another pause. Then the reply:\n
- No, are you crazy?! Six grand?! That's IMPOSSIBLE!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_2"><text>Agroprom. Some thugs are walking toward the stalkers' base.\n
- I ran off to the side for a second and saw a stalker's grave. You know what it says on the cross, boys?\n"Killed defending the rear entrance."</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_3"><text>A veteran stalker is lecturing the rookies:\n
- Right then! Stick together, stand by each other, don't screw your comrades over, don't go putting every filthy thing in your mouth... I had one "partner" here once, the bastard. Bandits caught us, lined us up against the wall, and started joking around: choose, they said, either please us, or we shoot you.\n
- So what did you say? ask the rookies.\n
- What did we say? That piece of shit agreed, and I... I got shot.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_4"><text>A thug, drunk out of his mind, is standing by a wall when he suddenly drops to the floor. He lies there and says:\n
- Fuck, boys, that wall is definitely trying to crush me. I'm telling you.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_5"><text>- Buddy, help me! came a shout to the stalker as he was walking past some bushes.\n
- What, you want a medkit? Hah! Bastard!\n
- Naaah... I ran out of paper!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_6"><text>A tired, blood-soaked stalker in an exoskeleton with a grenade launcher is dragging a pseudofish. Another one comes toward him:\n - Hey, pal! How's the fishing?\n
- Painful, damn it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_7"><text>A loner and a Freedom member meet one day. The loner asks him for a smoke, and the Freedom guy hands him a cigarette. The loner lights up and says:\n
- Hmm, this doesn't taste much like "Беломор [TERM?]"?!\n
The Freedom member replies:\n
- You'll laugh for a long time, but this isn't "Беломор [TERM?]".</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_8"><text>A black guy from the States came to the Zone to hunt mutants. He brought a top-notch gun and a top-notch suit with him. A day later they brought him to an ICU in Kyiv. The doctor asks him, "What happened?" He says, "Well, I ran out of water. And it was already night. I walked up to a tent, stuck my hand with the flask in there, and said: water... please give me some water!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_9"><text>A hunchbacked stalker is walking through Кровососовка [TERM?]. Suddenly, a voice in his head says: "Got a smoke, stalker?"\nNow he nearly craps himself and thinks: "Please don't touch me, I'm little, hunchbacked, and I don't smoke."\n
The voice again: "No, you're not hunchbacked."\n
Then the voice fades away...\n
The stalker runs back to base, up to a mirror, and the hump is gone.\n
So he goes to his lame friend and tells him there's this kind Controller in Кровососовка [TERM?]. \n
The friend heads there. Walks through the village. The voice says: "Hey, hunchback, got a smoke?"\n
"No, I'm not hunchbacked. That stalker before me, he was the hunchback. I'm lame."\n
"No, you're hunchbacked!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_10"><text>Two stalkers from Freedom decided to contribute to the study of the Zone. They bring Professor Sakharov a report on their experiments over at Yantar. He reads:\n
Experiment one: Caught a tushkano, whistled, the tushkano ran away.\n
Experiment two: Caught a tushkano, tore its legs off, whistled, the tushkano did not run away.\n
Conclusion: A tushkano without legs can't hear.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_11"><text>- Why's Vasyan so jumpy?\n
- Because of an artifact...\n
- What artifact?\n
- You don't know? Vasyan found a really rare artifact. It's called "Сердце друга [TERM?]." It's in two parts. You keep one for yourself and give the other one away. After that, everything gets shared between you: joy, pain, sorrow!\n
- So what?\n
- He's on his period.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_12"><text>The stalkers are sitting by the campfire, warming up, bored. Another one walks over:\n
- Hey, boys! Why are you sitting here staring at the sky? - he pulls a bundle from his backpack. - Here, check out the dope.
The stalkers perk up and start rubbing their hands. It goes around the circle:\n
- Oh, excellent!\n
- S-s-s-so gooood!\n
- Nah, kind of average.\n
- I've had better.\n
- What are you talking about, boys? It's nothing but wood chips. I didn't feel a thing! says the rookie.\n
- There you go, you ruined the whole buzz, you idiot! You're in the Zone! Is it that hard to imagine it's dope and not sawdust?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_13"><text>- Кандёха [TERM?], fuck this Zone. Let's head back to the neighborhood and hustle!\n
- No-o-o, I need to get to the Monolith. I've got one personal wish...\n
- A half-arm-long dick?\n
- Fuck... how the hell did you know?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_14"><text>A boar is chasing a Flesh and thinking:\n
- Can Sidorovich really run faster than me?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_15"><text>Some rookies are sitting by the campfire, dreaming:\n
- Ah, once we move up a little, run some jobs, and make some cash. We'll buy ourselves top-notch gear, tricked-out guns, and head North. They say the artifacts there are worth their weight in gold. We'll get rich, get out of the Zone, buy some real cars, and go relax in the Канары [TERM?], over there in Таити [TERM?]. Ever been to Таити [TERM?]?\n
Suddenly a Bloodsucker leaps at the rookies, grabs them by the ears, and smashes their heads together hard. Skulls crack. The Bloodsucker licks his lips:\n
- Таити [TERM?], Таити [TERM?]! We've never been to any Таити [TERM?]! They feed us just fine right here!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_16"><text>A thug walks past a wounded stalker.\n
Stalker: Help me, pal!\n
Bandit: No offense, buddy, I've only got one magazine left.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_17"><text>Attention everyone! Strange zombies have appeared in the Zone, floating along Припять [TERM?] in a kayak. The kayak usually contains two mysterious beings calling themselves Гребибля [TERM?] and Гребубля [TERM?]... And sometimes there's a third, no less mysterious creature called Кудатудабля [TERM?].</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_18"><text>A stalker who's completely wasted crawls up to the bar and says to the Barkeep:\n
- Hey, friend, put on that Валерий Меладзе [TERM?] song about Стоша Говнозад [TERM?] for the boys! 
- What are you talking about? There's no such song! says the Barkeep, surprised.\n
- How is there not? "Стоша Говнозад [TERM?], тихо на пальцах..."</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_19"><text>A stalker buys a bottle of vodka from the Barkeep and tries to open it, but can't.\n
- Hey, Barkeep! Why won't your bottle open?\n
- It's elementary! Find a "Crystal Thorn," pierce the cork through a "Pellicle," hook the other end onto a "Spring," stick three "Batteries" into the "Spring," press it, and the bottle will open!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_20"><text>A veteran stalker is sitting in the bar having a drink, and two rookies are sitting nearby. One of them keeps looking enviously at the stalker's snack and sighing, so the stalker says:\n
- Hey, tell your buddy to come join us, we'll sit a while.\n
The second replies:\n
- No, he's full.\n
- Then let him stop pissing himself and come have a drink.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_21"><text>A rookie is walking through the Zone at night. Suddenly something starts chirping.\n
- A cricket, the rookie thinks.\n
- Radiation, idiot, says the Controller sitting in the bushes.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_22"><text>- You hear about the incident at Duty's base?\n
- So what happened to them?\n
- A Controller got right into the radio room. Spent half an hour recruiting for "Грех [TERM?]."\n
- What's the point?\n
- Duty members are straightforward guys: if one of their own is recruiting, then it must be the right thing to do. They spent the whole day looking for this "Грех [TERM?]" so they could join it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_23"><text>One cheerful Controller in the Zone decided to check what would happen if he made a Bloodsucker drink a zombie's blood. In the end both died: the Bloodsucker from hunger, the zombie from being tickled...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_24"><text>A veteran stalker wound up in Hell, shrugged off his heavy gear, threw away his battered rifle, dropped to his knees, raised his hands up, and joyfully shouted at the top of his lungs: "Hura-a-a-a-ay, at last, the long-awaited rest!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_25"><text>Geneticists tried to combine a Chimera's invulnerability, a Bloodsucker's feeding method, and a Controller's abilities. That's how they recreated the mother-in-law!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_26"><text>An old Bloodsucker is teaching a young one:\n
- Don't go to the Cordon. The rookie stalkers there don't have money for anti-rad meds. They "treat" themselves with vodka. I ate one once and spent two days sick with a hangover afterward...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_27"><text>A zombie, dying:\n
- Piiiiss....\n
A stalker walks past:\n
- Well, damn... People ask for water when they're dying, and this one...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_28"><text>A Controller and three stalkers are sitting by the campfire.\n
Controller: "All right, the moment I wave my hand, everybody laughs".</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_29"><text>A rookie asks a veteran stalker:\n- You don't happen to know anywhere around here without pseudodogs? I'm afraid to sleep.\nVeteran:\n- Look, go straight ahead, then turn onto the road, then left, and you'll see a little village. You won't need to be afraid of dogs there.\nRookie:\n- Great! So why aren't there any?\n- They're afraid of Bloodsuckers.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_30"><text>There once were three stalker brothers. Two were smart, and the third was a fool: one day he'd take a shit in a "Whirligig," the next he'd piss in an "Electro"...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_31"><text>The tax inspector comes to see Sidorovich. They knock on the iron door:\n
- Does Sidorovich live here?\n
- No!\n
- Then who are we speaking to?\n
- Sidorovich.\n
- Then why are you saying he doesn't live here?\n
- You call this living?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_32"><text>On a dark, rainy night, a stalker is sneaking through the Zone and stumbles across one of his own, dozing under the open sky, with a rusty bus not far away.\n
- Hey, buddy, why didn't you spend the night in the bus?\n
- I did, but then a Controller kicked me out...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_33"><text>Two Freedomers are coming back from a hemp field. One suddenly spots a snail and stomps it with savage fury.\n
- What did it ever do to you, pal?! asks the other.\n
- It drove me fucking crazy, chasing me all day!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_34"><text>The Barkeep is talking to the Swamp Doctor.\n
- You don't know why Voronin's hair is so thick?\n
- He rubs eggs into it.\n
- Well, you're an acrobat...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_35"><text>A stalker walks into Sidorovich's cellar just as two men are robbing the old man. He rushed to the rescue...\n 
The haul had to be split three ways...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_36"><text>Stalker wisdom: "A word isn't a sparrow. Let one careless one fly out, and a whole three-story one comes flying back."</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_37"><text>A stalker went on a run once, saw a Flesh, and took a shot at it, but missed.\n
- Damn, I've gotten completely cross-eyed, he says, then glances around, sees nobody nearby, and adds:\n
- Though I always was.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_38"><text>The Barkeep and Wolf are arguing.\n
Barkeep: "A bundle of crowbars usually sinks."\n
Wolf: "But it floats perfectly well in mercury."\n
Barkeep: "But if the crowbars are uranium, they sink even in mercury."\n
Wolf: "Then you try sinking uranium crowbars in mercury."</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_39"><text>Only Russian and Ukrainian stalkers, hearing the words "one hundred grams," don't ask: "Of what?"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_40"><text>Freedomers are talking:\n
- Imagine this, Vasya drank some PROPER beer at the bar yesterday and felt like he was born again!\n
- No hangover?\n
- No, he was crawling, pissing himself, forgot how to talk...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_41"><text>One stalker says to another:\n
- I can hit a rat from 100 paces.\n
- Interesting. Where are you going to find rats that'll wait for you to measure out a hundred paces?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_42"><text>There's a sign hanging on the door in Sidorovich's cellar:\n 
"I've got everything a real stalker needs!"\n
And right below it, another one:\n
"And if I don't have something, then a real stalker doesn't need it!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_43"><text>Some stalkers are sitting by the campfire. One says:\n
- They slipped me another pair of shitty boots.\n
The second replies:\n
- That's not funny.\n
The first says:\n
- But it's true!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_44"><text>An announcement over Sidor's shack:\n
"New promotion! Buy two Kalashes, eight hundred rounds for them, three Makarov pistols, six magazines for each, twelve anti-rads (or sixteen bottles of vodka), eighteen medkits, and seven grenades, and get A BANDAGE ABSOLUTELY FREE!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_45"><text>A stalker is sitting by the campfire strumming a single chord on his guitar.\nA Controller sits down beside him and says with a smile:\n
- Well then, stalker, shall we start the concert by request?..</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_46"><text>A stalker walks up to a Freedom checkpoint and says:\n
- Why is there such a high fence around Freedom's base?\n
- So fools won't climb over it.\n
- Into it or out of it?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_47"><text>Vodka "Казаки [TERM?]" is like a Russian nesting doll: open one, and then comes the second, the third...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_48"><text>In Sidorovich's little cellar:\n 
- Sidorovich, do you have a conscience?\n
- We-e-ell... How much are you offering?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_49"><text>Two Freedomers are sitting together:\n  
- Ah, the weed just isn't what it used to be...\n 
A snork rides past on a bicycle.\n 
- Looks just right to me!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_50"><text>Two stalkers:\n 
- Why do you smell so bad?\n 
- Well, I spotted a "Night Star," and right next to it a Pseudogiant was sleeping with its back to me, so I crawled over to get it. 
- And?\n 
- And what? The giant was having nightmares! </text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_51"><text>Garbage. A stalker and a bandit are walking toward each other. The bandit pulls out a ПМ [TERM?], points it at the stalker, and asks:\n
- Got money?\n
The stalker pulls out an Абакан [TERM?], points it at the bandit, and says quite calmly:\n
- Why?\n
The bandit puts away the ПМ [TERM?] and pulls out a thousand-ruble note:\n
- Just wanted it changed!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_52"><text>Stalkers are sitting by the campfire... chatting... drinking... shooting the breeze...\n
A rookie walks over... sits down... takes off his boots... stretches them toward the fire... everyone freezes...\n
A minute of confusion... Then one of them asks:\n
- Listen... pal... do you even change your socks at all?...\n
And he replies:\n
- Sure I do... for two "Wrenched"...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_53"><text>Professor Sakharov's latest research has proven that so-called zombies are just stalkers who haven't cured their hangover yet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_54"><text>A dealer is walking quietly and peacefully toward Freedom's base with a sack of weed... Wham, into a "Springboard"!\n
One guard at the gate says to the other:\n
- What an asshole! Smoked it all on the way here again!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_55"><text>A knock at the shelter door.\n
- Who is it?\n
- It's me, the Bloodsucker!\n
- And?\n
- That's all...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_56"><text>A Pseudogiant is walking down the road. Suddenly a tushkano comes up to him and says:\n
- Take your pants off!\n
- Why? the Pseudogiant asks in surprise.\n
- Need to. What, are you sorry or something? the tushkano replies.\n
- Fine... the Pseudogiant grumbles.\n
The tushkano inspects them carefully from every side and says:\n
- Nah, these aren't mine. Mine had a little pocket...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_57"><text>A reporter in the sewers is interviewing a Bloodsucker:\n
- And what do you feed on?\n
- Pals, artifacts.\n
- What kind?\n
- Come on, I'll show you, PAL...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_58"><text>A young stalker runs up to a pseudodog and starts stroking its fluffy tail. A veteran shouts in horror:\n 
- What are you doing? It'll tear you apart!\n
- No, man, they don't bite from this end.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_59"><text>- Warrant Officer, guess what's heavier: a kilo of cotton or a kilo of scrap iron?\n
- A kilo of scrap iron, of course!\n
- Wrong. They weigh the same.\n
- Yeah? Let me crack you over the head first with a kilo of cotton, then with a kilo of scrap iron, and then you'll know which one's heavier.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_100"><text>Two stalkers are crawling across the perimeter. Suddenly one of them plants his hand in a pile of shit. The other starts laughing. The first one, clapping a filthy hand over his mouth:\n
- Quiet, you'll alert the military!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_60"><text>A Freedomer is sitting there smoking a joint when a zombie walks up to him:\n 
- Buddy, let me take a drag.\n
The guy calmly lets him, and the zombie shuffles off after taking a puff.\n 
Then he sits there wondering why the guy wasn't scared... So he rips off one arm and one leg. Walks up again:\n 
- Buddy, let me take a drag.\n
- Here.\n
The zombie shuffles off again and wonders why the guy still wasn't scared.\n
He tears off his remaining leg and rips open his belly. Walks up to the Freedomer again.\n
- Buddy, let me take a drag.\n
- No-o-o-o, from the look of it, that's bad for you...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_61"><text>Duty's checkpoint in front of the Bar. From the Wild Territory side come a terrible roar, wild gunfire, whining pseudodogs, and an inhuman bellow:\n
- F*ck!!! Holy sh*t!!! C*cks in your mouth!!! Stop the f*ck still!!! You f*ggot pricks!!! Bite the damn heel off already!!!\n
Then silence. Around the corner comes Sakharov, politely adjusting his gas mask, and addresses everyone:\n
- Sorry. I was upset...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_62"><text>At Garbage, in the hangar.\n
A veteran stalker, looking dead serious, is dragging himself toward the toilet out in the yard, hauling an enormous heavy backpack with him. The backpack's stuffed full: brand-new guns still covered in grease, ammo sorted into boxes, a heap of artifacts each wrapped in its own little bag, his whole suit, everything.\n
From inside the hangar comes a rookie stalker's voice:\n
- Buddy, why are you dragging your backpack into the toilet?\n
- I'm in that kind of mood. Feel like taking a shit on my whole life.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_63"><text>I'm walking up to the checkpoint by the bridge, looking for Kuznetsov, and from there I hear:\n
- Hey, stalker! Come here, we'll talk! Got canned food, we'll eat! Got fire-water, we'll drink! Got a tambourine, then however, we'll sing! shouted Private Худайбердыев [TERM?]...\n
UKRAINE IS AN INDEPENDENT DEMOCRATIC STATE, however...</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_64"><text>Two rookie stalkers are walking through the Zone. One says to the other:\n
- Listen, I heard some bandit yelling about olives. I absolutely love olives. Shall we go catch some?!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_65"><text>Some Duty members are sitting by the campfire. One says:\n
- I'm giving us away...\n
- Why, you traitor!\n
shouts another one, extra vigilant, shooting the first in the head.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_66"><text>A Freedomer comes to see the Doctor.\n
- Feeling like shit, Doc!\n
The Doctor listens to him and says:\n
- You ought to drink some herbs, my good man.\n
- Maybe I should smoke some syringes while I'm at it?
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_67"><text>A drunk stalker crawls into "Сто рентген [TERM?]" on all fours. He turns toward the left wall and starts crawling up it. Then he climbs across the ceiling, slides down the other wall to the counter, orders a bucket of vodka, downs it in one go, turns around, and crawls back out the same way.\n
One stalker says to another:\n
- DID YOU SEE THAT?!\n
- Yeah. Didn't even have a chaser!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_68"><text>Some Duty men line the thugs up against a wall.\n
The warrant officer commands: "Ready!"\n
Commands: "Aim!"\n
Suddenly one of the thugs sneezes loudly.\n
The firing squad, in unison:\n
- Bless you!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_69"><text>Voices in the Zone:\n
- So what are we going to do with you?\n
- Comrade Pseudogiant, excuse me, I didn't know the underbarrel grenade launcher wouldn't take you down with the first shot...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_70"><text>Military briefing before a raid into the Zone:\n
- You have accidentally stepped into a "Whirligig" anomaly. Your actions?\n
- Rise twenty meters into the air, then scatter in pieces over a wide area.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_71"><text>Two Bloodsuckers are sitting there with a bottle of vodka. A stalker walks by.\n
- Hey, stalker, will you be our third?\n
- I will!\n
- Excellent. We've already drunk the other two.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_72"><text>- You hear about the incident at Duty's base?\n
- So what happened to them?\n
- A Controller got right into the radio room. Spent half an hour recruiting for "Грех [TERM?]."\n
- What's the point?\n
- Duty members are straightforward guys: if one of their own is recruiting, then it must be the right thing to do. They spent the whole day looking for this "Грех [TERM?]" so they could join it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_73"><text>An old stalker and a young stalker are chatting by the campfire. The young one asks:\n
- Listen, do you think a soul can catch cold?\n
- Ah, youngsters these days are so ignorant... Just think about it: how can a "Soul" catch cold if it's an artifact?\n
- Strange, strange... the young one replies. I heard this in Sidorovich's cellar: "My soul, put your slippers on, the concrete floor is cold, you'll catch cold..."
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_74"><text>A Freedomer is standing on the bank of Припять [TERM?], smoking a joint and staring at the waves, muttering:\n
- Fishy, fishy, give me a new house, a woman with everything in the right place, and more food! Come on, don't be stingy!\n
One of the egghead ecologists walks by:\n
- What are you standing here for? You know fish don't talk!..\n
A huge gold fish sticks its head out of the water and says:\n
- That's exactly what I've been telling this idiot for the last damn hour! Read too much Pushkin, you stoned pothead!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_75"><text>A stalker is walking through some ruins, sees a door with a skull and crossbones and red letters saying, "Don't go in, it'll kill you!"\n
He went in.\n
It killed him.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_76"><text>Major Kuznetsov and his greenhorns on the Cordon are doing a crossword:\n
- Night duty starting with a P?\n
- Patrol?\n
- No, doesn't fit the letters...\n
- Picket?\n
- No, what are you talking about, that's not the official term!\n
- Post?\n
- Comrade Major, look on the last page!\n
- Pajamas!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_77"><text>Two stalkers are drinking vodka. A third one walks up:\n
- Oh-ho! Vodka! I'll be the third!\n
- No, the fourth. We've already sent three on ahead.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_78"><text>The lack of vodka is vodka's only flaw.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_79"><text>A stalker tossed a sock at the ceiling and it stuck there. "A gravitational anomaly," the experienced stalker thought.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_80"><text>Two drunk stalkers are walking through the swamp (well, crawling, to be exact). Suddenly a Snork rushes past on all fours. One stalker says to the other:\n
- L-l-listen, buddy, I don't get it! Look at that drunken bum. Did we drink brake fluid or something?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_81"><text>A veteran stalker is walking through the woods when out of nowhere a huge Chimera appears in front of him and says in a terrible voice:\n 
- Well, veteran, has the powder in your flask gotten damp yet?!\n
Right then the veteran's powder got damp...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_82"><text>One day Swamp Doctor is walking through the Zone with his dog, when a stalker comes toward him:\n
- Hey, Doctor! Why doesn't your dog bark? He lets strangers get awfully close.\n
- Well, think it through yourself: if a pseudodog doesn't let strangers get close, how is it supposed to eat them?
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_83"><text>A group of hard-case Freedomers is heading out of the Zone toward the Cordon, bristling with weapons, all in exoskeletons.\n
Major Kuznetsov, after counting out the cash due at the usual rate, asks:\n
- You boys heading into town?\n
- Yeah...\n
- Mind taking the mail with you?\n
- What, you want us to seize the telegraph, the telephone, and the bridges too?!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_84"><text>A rookie stalker calls a friend. The friend answers in a languid voice:\n
- I won't talk to you. I've fallen into depression...\n
The rookie stalker thought: "I'll have to ask the veterans what kind of anomaly this depression is."
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_85"><text>A Freedomer walks up to a Duty man:\n
- Sir, you are a scoundrel! I demand satisfaction and challenge you to a duel! I grant you the choice of weapons: assault rifle or knife?\n
- Knife.\n
- Excellent. Then I choose the assault rifle!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_86"><text>- Pseudogiant, do you love nature?\n
- Yea-a-a-a-a-a-a-ah!\n
- Even after what it did to you?
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_87"><text>On Tuesdays and Thursdays, toward evening, Sidorovich would hang out a sign reading "Break for German lesson" and lock the bunker.
Late stalkers would kick the rusty door in annoyance while muffled phrases drifted through it: "Ja, ja! Das ist fantastisch!".
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_88"><text>A soldier caught a stalker at the perimeter:\n
- Now I'll show you how to sneak into the Zone!\n
- Phew, thank God, because this is already the third time they've caught me! 
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_89"><text>Three Freedomers are sitting by the campfire... Nothing to do... bored to death... so they decide to play Russian roulette. The first pulls out a round, loads it, pulls the trigger. Bang. Drops. The second pulls out a round, loads it. Bang, drops. The third keeps watching, then pulls one out, loads it, fires. The last thought in his head:\n
"Do they really play roulette with a Makarov?"
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_90"><text>Relations between stalkers and the military.\n
Checkpoint: "Halt, who goes there?"\n
Stalker: "Friendlies, with a bottle!"\n
Checkpoint: "Friendlies, move along! Bottle, halt!"
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_91"><text>Cocktail: "Three Fleshes"!\n
Recipe:\n
A crate of vodka and three stalkers...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_92"><text>A stalker reached the Monolith.\n 
Monolith: "I will grant 3 of your wishes..."\n
Stalker: "Well, fig me!.." (and figs, the exotic fruit, started raining down on him).\n
Stalker: "Pancakes... what the horseradish..." (and pancakes started raining down on him, and horseradish, the seasoning, fell on him).\n
Stalker: "THIS IS SHIT!"
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_93"><text>A female Pseudogiant is chasing tushkanos around a clearing. She runs and runs, trying to catch them, but they keep getting away. She gets tired, goes berserk, and tears after them roaring: "Hold still, you tampons!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_94"><text>Two stalkers:\n
- Every day you look more and more like a drunk.\n
- Why's that?\n
- Because your hands shake whenever you lift a bucket of vodka to your mouth!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_95"><text>A Controller is walking through the Zone, leading three pseudofleshes behind him. The first runs along shouting:\n 
- B... B... Br... Bya... B...\n
The second:\n
- Boo... Brooo... Boo...\n
The third keeps up and chimes in:\n
- Byyy... Bryyy... Byii... By...\n
The Controller sighs:\n
- Could really use a broad...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_96"><text>Two Freedom guys are sitting there smoking with a sack of weed.\n 
- Heh-heh, l-l-listen, Колян [TERM?], heh-heh, what'll happen to me if I smoke the whole sack at once?\n
- Well, you'll start bleeding from your nose, eyes, ears.\n
- Damn, no kidding... why?\n
- Because if you smoke the whole sack by yourself, you bastard, I'll smash your face in!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_97"><text>Two Jewish stalkers are walking along:\n
- Мойша [TERM?], did you know Сёма [TERM?] is a fag!\n
- What, he borrowed vodka and won't give it back?\n
- No, in the good sense...
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_98"><text>A stoned Freedomer is lying by the river:\n
- Beaver, why are your teeth so white?!\n
- You need to smoke less if you're talking to beavers!
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_99"><text>Stalkers are sitting by the campfire bragging.\n
Duty member: "This evening I saved some rookie out of an anomaly."\n
Mercenary: "And at lunchtime I helped one rookie fight off some bandits."\n
Freedomer: "Well, this morning I got one sad rookie high..."
</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_101"><text>- Hey! What was good while I was gone? \n
- Everything was good while you were gone.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_jokes_info_102"><text>In the psych ward, former stalkers are watching the morning Zone news on TV. One of them suddenly slaps his knee: \n
- Good thing I'm in the loony bin! \n
Behind his back, the orderlies say to each other: \n
- Yeah... Looks like this one's cured.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_103"><text>Attention, sensation! A Freedomer raised by dogs has been found in the Zone! Interestingly, he's the only well-mannered Freedomer in the Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_104"><text>A young Bloodsucker asks an old one: \n 
- How do you hunt stalkers? \n
- Well, first I let him spot me, then I make a big circle around him, then a slightly smaller one, and only then do I run up and grab him. \n
- I get it. But why run circles when you can sneak up from behind and grab him right away? \n
- Sure, you can do it that way too, but then you'll have to eat him with all the shit still inside him. </text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_105"><text>A stalker wandered around Freedom's base and asked: \n
- Guys, how do you even entertain yourselves around here? \n
- We've got a cook. Every Sunday we put him in a dress and take him dancing with the whole base. \n
- Well, that's not for me, the stalker says. \n
- Our cook says the same thing, that's why we do it with the whole base. </text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_106"><text>A Duty member walks into the deep woods and sees a Controller with his face smashed in, sitting there crying. \n
- What's wrong with you? \n
- Stalkers keep coming through here, and every one of them wants to mess with me. There aren't any women in the Zone, so every last one wants to have his way with me. \n
- Then fight back, the Duty man says. \n
- How am I supposed to fight back when they're loaded with weapons and threatening me with grenades? \n
- Then yell for help. \n
- I do yell! But who's going to hear me? It's the middle of nowhere out here! \n
The Duty man stood there, looked left, looked right, scratched his stubble, and started pulling off his suit.
Controller: \n
- E-e-eh... What are you doing? \n
- So you're saying it's the middle of nowhere out here?.. </text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_107"><text>A stalker is walking through the Zone and sees a Bloodsucker. \n
- What are you snorting for? \n
The Bloodsucker says nothing. The stalker smacks him around and moves on. \n
Another stalker comes along and sees the Bloodsucker. \n
- What are you huffing for? \n
The Bloodsucker says nothing. The stalker smacks him around and moves on. \n
Yet another stalker comes along and sees the Bloodsucker. \n
- What are you sitting there for? \n
The Bloodsucker says nothing. The stalker smacks him around and moves on. \n
An annoyed voice from behind: \n
- What are you sitting for, what are you snorting for... I live here, damn it! </text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_108"><text>A veteran Duty man walks in on some bandits. \n
- Well, well! Look who's rolled up! Buddy, got a smoke? \n
- I already explained to you last time, in plain language, that I don't smoke. \n
- Sorry, buddy, didn't recognize you. My eye's swollen shut, and anyway I only just came around and got back on my feet after your last visit.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_109"><text>A Bloodsucker walks into the bar and asks for beer. The stunned Barkeep: \n
- Ye-e-eah... Bloodsuckers don't come in here very often... \n
- No wonder! Beer is ten bucks!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_110"><text>A Bloodsucker is walking through the desert, and coming toward him are Петька [TERM?] and Василий Иваныч [TERM?]... \n
- Got anything fresher?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_111"><text>Two stalkers walk into the bar and see a notice: "Buying Bloodsucker heads. One head - 100$". \nThey turn right around and head for the Wild Territory. They search until nightfall. Finally they spot a Bloodsucker standing there. They quickly drop it with two barrels, cut off its head, and camp nearby for the night... \nIn the morning, one wakes up, climbs out of his sleeping bag, and sees ten Bloodsuckers standing all around their camp. Tentacles spread out, eyes gleaming, growling nasty. The stalker quickly shakes the next sleeping bag and wakes his friend up happy: \n
- Get up, pal - we're rich!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_112"><text>- What's the difference between Tushkanos in Africa and Tushkanos in the Zone?  \n
- If you meet Tushkanos in Africa, they run away from you. If you meet Tushkanos in the Zone, you run away from them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_113"><text>Stalkers are sitting by the campfire swapping stories. One says: \n
- So I'm walking through Red Forest one time. Suddenly I see blind dogs surrounding me... \n
- And then what? \n
- I see things are bad. So I climb the nearest tree, quick as I can... \n
- And then? \n
- I'm sitting in the tree, and the dogs are pacing around below, snapping their teeth. Then suddenly the branch under me goes crack! \n
- And? \n
- What do you think? They damn well ate me!</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_114"><text>The Bar. The door flies open and a Chimera walks in, holding a thousand-ruble note in its teeth. It goes up to the counter, puts the money down, and says: \n
- Vodka and a tomato! \n
The unflappable Barkeep pours vodka into a bowl and puts a tomato beside it. The Chimera laps up the vodka, eats the tomato, and leaves at its own pace. The Bar is frozen with shock. Suddenly a drunk stalker's voice comes from the corner: \n
- No, did you see that? Chasing vodka with tomatoes?</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_115"><text>A Controller appeared near the bar. Got in everyone's way, grabbed people's brains now and then. One stalker was given a job to clear out the Controller. One day he was gone, two days, three. That's it, everyone thinks, the Controller zombified him. They were just about to send scouts when here comes that stalker, drunk off his ass. He goes into the bar and orders a crate of vodka and snacks. Leaves. Again he's gone one day, two days, three. On the fourth day he comes into the bar, swaying, and says: \n
- That's it, Barkeep, the Controller won't be coming back. \n
- You mean you drank with him and worked something out?
- No, Barkeep, I was drinking with my friend Федька [TERM?]. I showed the Controller a photo of my mother-in-law. You should have seen him run when he saw that picture.</text></string>
<string id="dm_jokes_info_116"><text>Marked One bursts into Sidorovich's cellar, pulls out a hundred bucks, and casually tosses it onto the table. \n
- Give me meds for all of it! \n
- No, Marked One, I am not tearing one little bandage into four pieces.</text></string>

<string id="dm_action_info_0"><text>What is there to do here anyway? This is basically kindergarten, a nursery. Sure, if you don't hang around here a bit, the Zone will finish you in five minutes flat. A smart man gets his edges knocked off first, then climbs into the devil's own backyard. Besides, you can get hold of gear or a weapon here, no problem. Everyone does.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_1"><text>If I could just wait for these uniformed pretty boys to take a lunch break... No point sitting here; I need to get back to the mainland, and these bastards won't let us through. I'm not the only one itching for the exit, but so far we still can't slip past.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_10"><text>The boys in uniform needed something nearby. Nobody used to come here at all; everything was stripped clean before I ever showed up, even the cables were cut out. And now they found something, looks like... I couldn't even get close to the building. They spotted me right away and opened fire. At least I got out without another hole in my hide.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_100"><text>Back off. Trying to survive, that's all.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_11"><text>We're putting together a team of men who aren't afraid to go underground in the Zone. There's an old plant, and all kinds of service tunnels under it; they say there's plenty down there, always something to profit from. Interesting, too...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_12"><text>Still thinking... They say Strelok's main base used to be somewhere around here... Makes me curious. Maybe there are still traces from back then, if you look hard enough?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_13"><text>I need to step away for a bit... Damn it, I nearly got nailed an hour ago! I was here half a year back, quiet as a grave, and now there are shaved-heads in tracksuits under every damn bush! Unreal...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_14"><text>You're lucky, stalker, that the bandits didn't catch you warm: they've got a base right nearby. Ah, if it were up to me, I'd hit it hard... For now we're just watching. That's their support point; the main one is closer to the center of the Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_15"><text>They say there used to be a serious laboratory here, classified. Ah... On the one hand, if we could find the entrance, there must be loot in there. On the other, it feels damn sketchy...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_16"><text>Need to look around first. You know the present-day Dark Valley had a research complex before the disaster, an underground one at that? I don't know what it was for, but I doubt it was anything good. People tell all kinds of stories about it, mostly bad ones. Scary ones, even.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_17"><text>What? What do you want to hear? I'll tell you this: the Duty grunts may be cops, sure, but they know how to keep order, I'll give them that. Still don't like them. Everywhere they act like they own the place: don't take that, don't carry this out of the Zone... On top of that, they've already decided what you can say on the mainland and what is forbidden. Word is they want to destroy the Zone bit by bit. Soldiers, even former ones, don't surprise me... dreamers. Worse thing is, they say they've got support from the very top.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_18"><text>We will maintain order! This territory is now controlled by Duty, and the law here is Duty's rules. We control the Zone's borders and cool off hot heads: lunatics come here by the trainload, romance lovers... then die in bunches on the very first day.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_19"><text>Nothing from me, but I advise you to look around. Have you been to our transit base? It isn't only ours, truth be told; you can meet all kinds there. Main thing is, the place is good, clean of filth, and all the news from the Zone flows through it. You can almost always hear something useful, or just chew the fat with people about life.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_2"><text>I want to rest. You should head to the camp too; you'll hear all the rumors there. Everyone on their first time in, rookies like you, usually stops by us to pick up some experience or rest a little. We've got soldiers posted nearby. Don't be too scared of them, but don't show yourself too much either; they might shoot, easy as breathing. Not far from the trader, the local middleman, there's a place where you can set up a quiet little camp.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_20"><text>You should drop by the Bar and talk to people. Right now it's safe, stalker, and we're trying to keep it that way. There's always a crowd here: some have settled in for good and don't go beyond the nearby area, others are preparing for the next raid. Shame Ирокез [TERM?] never came back. He liked setting first-timers like you on the right path.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_21"><text>Heard Duty announced recruitment into its proud ranks? I thought about it for a minute, then decided: why the hell would I need that, back on the belt every other day? Discipline, this and that... I already served my two years, and that was enough...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_22"><text>We're heading out on a raid soon. And if you haven't heard yet, I'm telling you: we've announced additional recruitment. If you've got more or less some experience, come by. You won't regret it. Ask for Petrenko at the base.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_23"><text>I ought to drop by the arena... You came to watch the fights too, maybe place a little bet?.. Well now! There's an arena around here somewhere, and you know nothing. So here's the deal: Duty members catch mutants, right? After the research, if the beasts are still alive, they release them into the arena. And those little darlings come in all kinds: sometimes you can die laughing, sometimes you can piss your pants.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_24"><text>We just supplied the arena with fresh meat. Entertainment for the people, and no shame in us earning a cut from the bets. Besides, it proves to the stalkers one more time that Duty doesn't just flap its tongue, it actually does the work.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_25"><text>Listen, have you been to "Росток [TERM?]"? It used to be quiet there, but now going alone is rough: a proper wild field, too many mutants breeding. Come with me, eh?.. Though... I don't know you, and you don't know me. You never know. That's it, man, sorry. We split.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_26"><text>Nothing much... We just came from "Росток [TERM?]". I don't advise you to poke your nose in there, especially alone. Want to live? Then don't go.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_27"><text>I was thinking of heading to Yantar, then changed my mind. The eggheads have a real outpost of science there in the Zone. They're digging around, who knows in what, and zombies wander around the complex. Idyllic, by God.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_28"><text>We just got back... Recently cleared the Yantar area... yeah, carved up plenty of those sons of bitches! There are research laboratories there, but zombies are always thick around them. We regularly have to run over and help the scientists.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_29"><text>Maybe I should head to the warehouses... You know, by the old warehouses? Freedom's got a base there. They're carefree, decent guys; sitting with them over a bottle of something good is pure pleasure. And Duty doesn't keep darting around like they do near the Bar.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_3"><text>We're starting up a job again. There's an old factory nearby, and we keep driving the bandits out of it, over and over, but every time they come crawling back! Hasn't even been a month since the last time, and there they are again. Be careful around there...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_30"><text>We're organizing a raid. Freedom dug in behind the old warehouses... those stoned screwups, damn them...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_31"><text>I'm leaving, and you should leave too, while it still isn't night! By day it's more or less tolerable here, but once the sun goes down...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_32"><text>Stalker, leave! We're about to pull the cordon back. For now we only hold it during the day, and at night we leave. It's too damn bad here after dark.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_33"><text>You see, at night one must take shelter here, preferably behind good doors. During the dark hours we are effectively under siege.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_34"><text>Well, pal, I can see you're not in the know. At night you should be sleeping somewhere far away from here. Around here at night even a grenade launcher doesn't always help!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_35"><text>You know what? Let the Duty members, Freedomers, and marauders decide whose chunk this is and what they'll do with it. I don't give a damn! To hell with all of it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_36"><text>We're working here right now, stalker. There's already enough filth breeding around, and now these mercenary bastards and Freedom idiots are making life harder...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_37"><text>I must warn you that it is rather unsafe here even during the day. Shootouts happen from time to time; as far as I understand, there is some kind of confrontation between local bandit groups.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_38"><text>We've got plans... Listen, tell me this: by rights, this is our territory, yes? It's easier for us to hold back the filth coming from the center of the Zone, yes? Let the eggheads dig around, who's bothering them, but Duty and the marauders can get the hell out of here!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_39"><text>I'm heading to the stalkers... What, you don't know? They've worn a new path through here so they can sneak loot straight to the perimeter past the Duty patrols. From Yantar to here, then by the back ways to Agroprom, and that's it, you're there!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_4"><text>Nothing. I don't know a damn thing. Just scraping by, gathering enough for daily bread. Going deep into the Zone scares me, to hell with that. There's no work at home, my wife nags me... A man's got to live somehow, right? Here at Garbage, if you walk around for a day, you can gather a few small artifacts here and there. Enough to eat and drink, basically.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_40"><text>What are you doing here? Heading to Yantar, or trying to smuggle artifacts past the Bar on the quiet?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_41"><text>I will not conceal that your colleagues, the stalkers, occasionally offer us rather interesting anomalous formations, artifacts, as you call them. Due to their... let us say, uncertain control, these places are something like a busy smuggling trail.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_42"><text>Come on, man. We made this path so we don't have to run into the Duty officials if we want to make a trip to the mainland! Sure, they roam around here plenty, but while they still don't know a damn thing, at least you can get around them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_43"><text>I just came from Yantar. Thought I'd sell the scientists a few things, like always, but they've locked themselves in their bunkers and barely come outside even during the day now, except for the next chopper. So if you're headed there, turn yourself around. You're out of luck...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_44"><text>Some kind of research is being conducted in the Yantar area, but lately the zombies have been pressing in. That's why we're guarding the approaches.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_45"><text>I do not even know what to tell you. I had wanted to return to our complex, Yantar, I believe you know it. And now here we are: they say that if it was merely dangerous before, now getting through has become completely impossible. Perhaps they are exaggerating?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_46"><text>I was at Yantar, and science has withered badly there: flinching, hiding... They only stay alive thanks to what gets flown in by chopper. On the other hand, there really are plenty of zombies around there. Live among them for a week and you'll start flinching too. Not much of a place. Not very pleasant.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_47"><text>To hell with hanging around zombies! They've multiplied all over that damned complex, pushing in and pushing in. And there are more of them every day.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_48"><text>We're trying to stop the zombies from advancing out of the laboratory complex. Honestly, I wouldn't mind if you joined in. We're short on people...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_49"><text>You know, we collect various data ourselves... I personally study the main routes by which quasi-liv... that is, zombies, in your terminology, spread. Would you share your observations?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_5"><text>That's about it... Some people settle in at Garbage and pick up small stuff, some dig deeper into the Zone. The chunks out there are fatter, sure, but not everyone will stick his nose in. Rookies with no experience have no business there, and if they don't have decent gear either, that's lights out. No chance.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_50"><text>Have you shot at the zombies crawling out of the laboratory building yet? Just look at them: afraid of nothing, feel no pain. Brainless beasts, in a word!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_51"><text>I'm heading to the laboratory to apply for a job! Relax, man, kidding... If you wander in there, that's it, count yourself gone. Best case, you become a zombie.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_52"><text>I'm warning you: don't go into the laboratory. No, if you really want to, go ahead, I won't hold you by force. Just nobody comes back alive from there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_53"><text>You see... I would like to warn you. You should not go near the laboratory. No one should, actually: it involves drastic changes to the psyche and metabolism, and I am afraid they are completely irreversible.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_54"><text>There! Now I'll enlight... educate... save you, lost sheep, in short. So here it is, man: don't aim your skis at the laboratory complex. It's bad there, very bad. People disappear, and then sometimes they come to you at night. Only these aren't vampire fairy tales, but the plain truth about zombies. That's how it is.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_55"><text>Have you seen our smart ones, the cream of the United Nations? They've gotten nervous as hell lately. For them to take two steps from the base, they call in a whole regiment for protection, with APCs and choppers.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_56"><text>What's it to you? Stop pestering people with stupid questions and people won't hassle you either.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_57"><text>You understand, we usually do not leave the bunker without appropriate escort: environmental conditions do not permit it. I am something of an exception. I do not much care for large expeditions, all that bustle, the military... However, I am afraid I cannot tell you anything useful for now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_58"><text>I get a kick out of our cheerful science! It blows my mind, man!.. Usually it doesn't poke its nose out of the bunker. But when it does, like it did recently, then things get wild. Good Lord! Soldiers everywhere, choppers, armored vehicles! It would be even better if they dragged a battleship in here, or an armored train at least...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_59"><text>Third day I've been hanging around here, watching. There's a laboratory here, right? Nobody has gone into it since the beginning, and the Duty boys only cleared zombies above ground, but now they've stopped even that, right? But the scientists have started going in there. Means they found some way to protect themselves, hell knows from what... So I'm thinking I'll find out. There must be loot in that place you could shovel up.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_6"><text>In the last few days, beasts have been pouring out of the Dark Valley in whole packs. No idea what's driving them out of there, but they're charging like it's a fire. And the eastern sector has mutants breeding like bedbugs; all we can do is keep shooting them. That's the news.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_60"><text>For now I'm watching you... What are you looking for here? Planning to head into the laboratory too? Heard a little fairy tale about miracle devices and piles of artifacts? M-mother... when will you idiots finally die out?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_61"><text>I work here, young man. I simply work here, fulfilling my duty to science and humanity. And if you want to ask about the abandoned laboratory, whose secrets every stalker I meet suspects me of knowing, my answer is: I do not know and do not want to know! This subject does not interest me and never has, is that clear?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_62"><text>Maybe the brainiacs really did come up with some device, you never know. It is interesting, what's hidden in that damned laboratory. Even if there isn't any proper loot, it is still interesting. If only I could get in...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_63"><text>I'm thinking: maybe I should join Freedom? Their base is right there, in the former army warehouses... Why not? The people seem competent, and if they're a bit careless, that's even good. No one needs to crush me with discipline; I know what to do, this isn't my first month here...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_64"><text>We're getting ready to kick somebody's ass... You don't sympathize with Freedom by any chance, do you? Fine, fine, don't take offense. I think we'll soon pry them out of those warehouses. No organization, no discipline... A herd. A pack at best. And now they got it into their heads to twitch against us, NATO-fed bastards...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_65"><text>I want to talk to someone. I meet with one Duty man here when there's a truce. We chat. The man is smart, generally, but narrow-minded as a tank. You see, our philosophy is completely different: the Zone can only be tamed, assimilated, not destroyed. For that, we need open access to all information; sooner or later somebody will come up with something useful. And they go: "close it," "forbid it," "do not disclose"... Idiots, by God, idiots. On the other hand, it makes sense: when the whole state machine is behind you, you're not really supposed to think too much.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_66"><text>There's a little farmstead here. It used to be quiet, but now some kind of filth has bred there. Better to take the long way around, so that's what I'm doing... Look, I warned you.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_67"><text>Stalker, I want to warn you right away: Bloodsuckers have nested in the village for a long time now, maybe something even worse too, so be careful.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_68"><text>What is there to do here... There haven't been artifacts here for a long time, and Bloodsuckers used to live in those houses over there. We shot them out as best we could. Now I went that way and I can't make myself reach the place. Intuition, or whatever, but I can't go there, that's all. No way. Death is there...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_69"><text>I'm getting the hell out of here! Did four weeks on Барьер [TERM?], and that's it, I've had enough! Some kind of filth has been coming from the Brain Scorcher side around the clock, and every day it pushes harder...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_7"><text>A lot of people have become "garbage pickers" now. Used to be nobody even looked in those heaps; the radiation would hard-boil your balls in half an hour. But now, with loot getting scarce, they wrap themselves in protection, take some chems, and go digging anyway. You can find all kinds of things there, though mostly small stuff.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_70"><text>If you're heading to our defense line, I respect you. If not, get out of sight! We need real men, not screwups. We've got enough of our own...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_71"><text>You heading to the defense line, man? That's good then. At least one more normal person shows up. We set the whole thing up and held it pretty well... but then the beasts came po-o-ouring in!.. It's rough now, so every gun helps.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_72"><text>What, you haven't heard? The path to the center of the Zone is open! Maybe it opened on its own, maybe someone helped it along, and honest thanks to him. Now it's time to rake in the prime loot!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_73"><text>You should wait, stalker. Don't run after everyone else. Tell me this: do you know what's there? Right, you don't. You don't know whether there's anything to profit from there or not. You don't know what traps are there either. So why the hell are you charging in like a herd of moose?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_74"><text>The path to the center is open, got it?! Straight road to the center now! Everyone is about to pile in there. Main thing is to be among the first and squeeze out the best stuff for yourself!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_75"><text>Move it, you'll see everything yourself! Don't you want to see for yourself what's going on farther in? Then you're really... touched. There must be so much there! Say, have you heard about Исполнитель желаний [TERM?]?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_76"><text>I'm not doing anything... Like children, by God! "Исполнитель желаний [TERM?]," "Klondike of artifacts"... It's laughable just listening to it!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_77"><text>I want to know myself what's beyond the horizon, man! What if we can explain all this shit they call the Zone in one shot?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_78"><text>See the apartment blocks? That's Припять [TERM?] already. Right behind it is the station. Ah, if only I could get there... except nobody knows what's wandering among those buildings now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_79"><text>I'll explain. There is Припять [TERM?]. Past Припять [TERM?] is the CNPP. What is going on there now, and what lives there, nobody knows. This is the place for us. There will be things to sort out, same as always.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_8"><text>Not a clue! I'm just heading to the Bar to talk to people. What, you've never been there? You're something else! Here's the deal: from where you're standing, go straight north. You won't make it two steps before there's the Bar. It's useful to stop in there in general, and for rookies like you it's just what the doctor ordered: experienced men hang around there sometimes, they'll tell you what's what. Only thing is, our Duty vigilantes will meet you on the way... Well, whether they like the look of you or not, that's how the cards fall.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_80"><text>Припять [TERM?]! Pinch me! Finally! The station is almost within arm's reach from here. Hell knows who you might run into here now, though, what kind of beast has its teeth sharpened for you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_81"><text>Friend, listen... Do you hear a voice in your head too, or have I just lost my mind? It keeps droning on and on...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_82"><text>Another one... All right. I will explain for the umpteenth time what kind of telepathic influence people are subjected to here. Voices inaudible from outside constantly call them to the center of the Zone and promise to fulfill any wish of whoever manages to touch... what was it... ah, yes, some kind of monolith.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_83"><text>You hear the voice? Funny, like a player in your head! Shame there's only one track: come to me, it says, and great happiness will be yours. Two hours now, same thing over and over.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_84"><text>Like you haven't guessed? You're breaking through to the station yourself! And so are we, what other news do you need?! If only we could clear those possessed idiots off the road...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_85"><text>The station grounds are very close! We still can't overcome the Monolith members' resistance!..</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_86"><text>There it is, the CNPP, within arm's reach. Almost nothing left, and these stubborn bastards won't let us through! Doesn't matter, we'll straighten them out now!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_9"><text>Listen, friend, do you know anything about Agroprom? I wanted to go there, but people laughed me down: they say there's not a damn thing left there, it was picked clean back when only anomalies were left. Do you know if they're telling the truth, or just having a laugh? I'm new around here, I believe it when locals talk... Maybe they got together and pulled one over on me? Give those bastards half a reason and they'll laugh themselves sick!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_94"><text>Stop! Make haste, but don't rush too much. Monolith members are all over here; they know the city inside and out, planted ambushes everywhere. Need to be careful.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_95"><text>Warning: most of the city is currently controlled by the Monolith faction. There are many ambushes; they have studied this place like the backs of their hands. Stay alert and check your weapon one extra time.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_96"><text>Ah, what I'd gladly do is carpet-bomb this little city. Bastards... they must be dug in everywhere except the sandboxes and flowerpots. How many people have already died because of these assholes!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_97"><text>Listen, who the hell knows about this Исполнитель [TERM?]... Maybe it isn't eternal, so there won't be enough for everyone? And what then, get down on all fours? You, kid, if we make it, you'll be behind me. I promise you that...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_98"><text>Duty must break through to the center, if not first, then among the first! Just imagine, stalker, some psycho, and almost all of you here are one way or another schizophrenics, paranoids, and morons, reaches some piece of crap that really can grant any wish. Huh? And then what?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_99"><text>News of the century: everyone who can walk on his own and hold a weapon is here now! This is... anything you wish could come true here! Just grasp the subject, friend, huh? Anything you wish! And then someone goes and says: "I want the Zone to vanish, now and ever, and unto ages of ages." Huh? Appreciate the scale of the tragedy? We'd all be left with nothing then. Every last one of us!</text></string>


<!-- Новички -->

<string id="dm_cool_info_0"><text>New? What the hell do we need new for when you can shovel the old shit forever and still not clear it out? The bandits have gotten completely bold, the bastards! When it comes to darting between anomalies for artifacts, that's us, but when it comes to taking someone else's loot... Ugh, scum! Watch you don't wander into Garbage. That's their favorite place.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_1"><text>I'm stuck here, stuck, you understand? I want to go home, and they won't let us through. That's all the news... The people who go deep into the Zone, the hardened ones, they do tell all kinds of stories. And sometimes they bring back loot that makes you jealous. They say there are places out there like gold fields: take all you want. Not everyone reaches them, though, and even fewer come back with a profit.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_6"><text>The soldiers are up to something. Searching, digging... Used to be choppers only flew to Yantar, guarding scientists, hauling supplies and equipment. Now it's a real invasion. They've started running sorties, driving around in APCs. They've already been spotted at Agroprom, and in Dark Valley too. No idea.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_7"><text>They say someone tried to get through the Scorcher again. Gone for good, obviously, man's finished... You haven't heard of the Brain Scorcher? Come on, man! It's the biggest bogeyman in the whole area! Only problem is, the horrors people tell about it are mostly true.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_8"><text>Besides the bandits, soldiers have started roaming around here too. Used to be you'd see a helicopter once in a hundred years, and now they've spread across almost the whole Zone. Lost something, maybe?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_9"><text>I want to warn you, stalker. The military has gone half-mad lately. They used to quietly guard the scientists, but now it's like someone twisted their tail: running around, rushing everywhere... They're not exactly peaceful. They've fired on your kind more than once, and we've had two wounded this week.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_10"><text>Выдра [TERM?] got killed at the Scorcher a week ago. If he had been a rookie, some headless greenhorn, sure, I'd understand. But he'd been stalking for years. They say he was even in Strelok's group. And there you have it...</text></string>
<!-- <string id="dm_cool_info_100"><text>Да я как-то и не в курсе последних событий.</text></string> -->
<string id="dm_cool_info_11"><text>Tell me this, stalker: why do you loners sometimes blow your roofs off? Not enough proper discipline, maybe? One of you decided to go past the Scorcher last week. Experienced man, they say... There are easier ways to lose your brains: barrel in your mouth and pull the trigger!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_12"><text>Those bastards... mercenaries. They've been drinking our blood for a long time, and now they've switched to the eggheads too. What the hell do they need them for? Ransom? Or so they'll share their Nobel prizes?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_13"><text>The mercenaries have gotten very active in recent weeks. We also call them marauders. That's another kind of filth here, if you haven't heard. Like bandits, only experts in military matters. They always preferred attacking stalkers, and lately for some reason they've become more interested in scientists. Either way, keep your eyes open. It costs them nothing to put a hole in your head too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_14"><text>I heard in passing recently that the eggheads supposedly dug up something incredible. And now everyone is on edge at once: soldiers, mercenaries, and Duty members are not exactly lagging behind...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_15"><text>If you're asking about the same thing all of you have been pestering me with for the last two days, my answer is: go to hell! If I knew, and if they hadn't forbidden it, I'd tell you. But I don't know, I don't know a damn thing! What did those scientists find, where did our boss go? What's that got to do with me?! He's on leave, and he doesn't owe us a report.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_16"><text>Ha! Everyone here is on edge! Конфедерат [TERM?] came back from a raid with his group, and they brought artifacts, mother of God! Конфедерат [TERM?], of course, keeps quiet and won't spill, same as always, and his boys keep joking that they went to the Юконские прииски [TERM?] and panned a little... Bastards!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_17"><text>All kinds of filth have been pouring out from the Scorcher for several days now. People built a defense line near the old warehouses; for now, seems like they're holding. If it doesn't let up, we'll have to go reinforce them. What else can we do...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_18"><text>Heard people saying the Zone is growing? I think it's true. I saw some hideous beasts almost right at the perimeter, things you used to meet only closer to the center. Bad business, huh?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_19"><text>Maybe they're not lying about Bloodsuckers near the Zone border. But what does that have to do with the Zone getting bigger? A pack wandered in... we missed it, fine. We sometimes work for several days straight! And we do the job properly. Nobody beyond the perimeter is shouting yet: "Help, mutants are surrounding us!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_2"><text>It's all kind of grim, that's what. The other day Выдра [TERM?] vanished for no reason, I still can't believe it... You probably never even heard of Выдра [TERM?], have you? He was practically a professor, here since the first year, knew the whole Zone like the back of his hand... and still, look at that. There are experienced stalkers, sure, but the Zone takes them anyway. Some head back to the mainland by choice, too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_20"><text>Do you think Barkeep knows the details about what the scientists dug up? Listen, maybe he's in with science altogether? Lately he's been looking for more experienced stalkers and giving them strange jobs. Explains nothing, just says go here or there... and the places are dead, never smelled of good loot. So what is he looking for?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_21"><text>Something strange is going on. Zombies that used to be afraid to come into the light have spread all over the area. What the hell is that about?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_22"><text>The zombies have become more aggressive and mobile for some reason. We used to clear them out inside the complex from time to time, but now we only hold the approaches. But I didn't tell you any of that, got it?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_23"><text>Be careful, because these walking corpses have flooded the whole area. They are extremely aggressive. We are constantly on defense, night and day. So it is rather dangerous here, young man.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_24"><text>Ah, the eggheads probably cooked up something wrong in their laboratory. Used to be you could barely find a zombie anywhere, and now they're pouring out of the complex. Main thing is, they wander around like they lost something and are looking for it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_25"><text>There's a rumor going around that science actually talked one of ours into going down into the laboratory. Gave him some kind of... protective contraption... Nothing else, no details.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_26"><text>People say all kinds of things. They even say some maniac turned up, made a deal with the scientists, and crawled into the laboratory after something for them. What a stupid asshole!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_27"><text>Ah, here's the main joke of the week! The eggheads signed up one of yours for a fat fee, and he went into the laboratory with some device of theirs. A new sacrifice to science, damn it!..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_28"><text>I think something is brewing again. The eggheads dug up something that put everyone on edge. And along the way, life is going to get worse for you and me.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_29"><text>Who the hell knows. Only they're running us twice as hard as before: cordon here, sweep there... There are a whole order of magnitude more soldiers in the Zone now too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_3"><text>It's grim, that's what I'll say. There have always been plenty of people on the outskirts, half of them never go deep into the Zone at all, and there aren't enough artifacts for everyone. Even the laboratories and factories have had everything that could be broken out already stripped and hauled away. Soon there'll be nothing to do here at all except open a restaurant... with a view and exotic cuisine.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_30"><text>I do not even know what to tell you... Something is always happening here, but that is normal. On the mainland, of course, they do not see it that way, but you and I are, after all, currently in an anomalous zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_31"><text>The eggheads are sniffing something out. Hell knows what secret they've already dug up, but they're twisting the soldiers' tails something fierce! Those men are already combing Agroprom and Dark Valley, searching and searching...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_32"><text>More filth comes pouring from behind the Scorcher every day, and Duty members and Freedomers have decided to start snapping at each other again. So they wipe each other out, and then what? How long can we hold Барьер [TERM?] alone?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_33"><text>Mutants are trying harder and harder to slip past the defense line. Lately it's been rough. If certain people would cut out their screwing around, we'd handle them easily!..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_34"><text>Duty keeps shouting about its heroic deeds at the defense line. Who around here would believe them... We started this thing, we keep dragging it along, and plenty of loners like you stayed voluntarily too. And those... to hell with them, bastards!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_35"><text>I heard Duty has gotten real full of itself. Supposedly "we are volunteers who want to achieve safety and order in the Zone"... yeah, volunteers! Some sponsor supplied those volunteers with gear and guns that would make you sick with envy. These ones sold out too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_36"><text>What rumors are going around? I'll tell you without any rumors: soon there will be more order. We'll clean the Zone of beasts, and of certain bastards too...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_37"><text>Have you heard what the Duty boys are bragging they'll do to us? "Grind us to dust" is the mild version. This worries me... Especially since they say they've re-equipped first-class.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_38"><text>What news? We sit here, beasts come at us, we shoot them, and then they come again, only harder. True, military choppers passed through a few times... and it looked like they even flew past the Scorcher.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_39"><text>What could be new here... same old, same old. Mutants, Freedom... though now military helicopters have gotten into the habit of flying around. If only they'd fire at the beasts once. No, not a damn thing...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_4"><text>New... People say all kinds of things! Believe everything and you'd run out of belief. They say some veteran stalker, let me through or I'll break through, came from the inner regions, brought something never seen before, made a heap of money... I could invent a hundred stories like that for you myself!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_40"><text>I saw military choppers. Imagine it: they passed over us and went straight past the Brain Scorcher! So I thought, here they come raining down. Not a damn thing. They kept going, circled around there, then came back the same way. Nice move, huh?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_41"><text>Ah, now that there's a passage to the center... Just imagine how much wealth must be lying underfoot there!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_42"><text>Now that it is possible to pass to the center of the Zone relatively calmly, stalkers have flown there like flies to honey. Ye-e-eah... greed really is not humanity's finest quality.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_43"><text>Now this is life coming our way! By the time all those people from the Bar, especially from the perimeter, pull up, all the cream is ours! We'll gather the tastiest stuff, and let the others stock up on scraps.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_44"><text>They say it really exists, Исполнитель желаний [TERM?]. Someone has already managed to reach it and make a wish for everything he could...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_45"><text>Listen, pal, I know anything can happen in the Zone. Seen it myself. But these stories about a wish instantly granting your own hotel in the Caribbean are complete bullshit and nothing else.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_46"><text>What, you don't know?! Two of ours, the ones who rushed to the center before anyone else, actually broke through to Исполнитель [TERM?] and made their wish! They dreamed all their lives about islands in a warm sea, so now they're sunning themselves somewhere in the tropics, no doubt.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_47"><text>Миклуха [TERM?] turned up, the main Freedomer. Everyone thought he'd gone back to the mainland, but in reality he somehow managed to slip past the Scorcher with a small group. That's a real man!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_48"><text>One of Freedom's detachments was found in a previously inaccessible area. How did they manage to get through unharmed, then survive here for several weeks? It just doesn't fit in my head. Looks like we underestimated these boys.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_49"><text>Imagine that, our Миклуха [TERM?] turned up! Alive, and the boys with him survived too. They slipped past the brain-scrubber, then spent a month stuck here, unable to get out.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_5"><text>Something murky is brewing here. Rumor says the Duty commander, the big boss, didn't just leave the Zone on some business, but went to negotiate with Freedom. Then they should make peace openly, instead of breeding all this bullshit! This whole business smells bad, that's how it is. On the other hand, veterans say they once started fighting for a stupid reason too. Let's hope those office bastards from the mainland don't drag us all into some new meat grinder...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_50"><text>You hear?! The soldiers are rushing in to grab the ready-made prize, they'll be here any minute! They found out the Scorcher is done for and want to scoop up all the loot at once!..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_51"><text>Information just came through: a large-scale army landing at the station is planned. My advice to you: if you want to snatch even a little loot, hurry.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_52"><text>This is complete lawlessness! The corridor only just opened, they started clearing the station of all kinds of shit, and here you go, the soldiers are coming for everything ready-made! Damn it all, no shame and no conscience...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_53"><text>Here's what I don't understand: how did those Freedomers manage to hold out for a month? Do they have invisibility caps or something? It's a complete nightmare out here!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_54"><text>You understand what's going on here? No, really, I respect Миклуха [TERM?] even more now! Imagine that: lasting more than four weeks in this shit, and not losing a single man!..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_55"><text>Some people here have lost their minds. They always seemed like strong men, too, and now they're drooling like complete idiots. Scary.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_56"><text>As one approaches the station, the unknown telepathic influence intensifies. Some have begun losing their minds, others are suffering disorders and visions. Perhaps now is the right time to fall back a little...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_57"><text>Listen, people here are really losing their roofs. Somebody sees a little stone and suddenly starts yelling that it's his artifact, that he spotted it first and everyone else can go south. Another man sees Джа [TERM?] appear on a cloud, arm in arm with squadmates who vanished hell knows how many years ago... No, something seriously unhealthy is happening here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_58"><text>Listen to this joke about a Controller. An old Controller is teaching a young one: "See that little soldier standing at his post way over there? Belt tight, uniform new, boots shiny: that's called a 'rookie.' You can take control of him from right here, but there's no point: he shoots badly, fears everything, no meat on him, just skin and bones. And over there, see that fighter smoking? Uniform worn, boots scuffed: that's called a 'scoop.' So-so prey, hard to take under control, shoots well, always alert, and plenty of meat, but stringy. Best to take him at night, when he dozes off. And way over the-e-ere, see that soldier sleeping under the bush, no belt, barefoot? That's an 'old-timer.' Lots of meat, fatty, but hell if you can get near him; he doesn't sleep at night and can crush you with his bare hands. You take him when he goes to the settlement for moonshine or drags himself into the Zone for loot. And over there, see that soldier walking, belt tight, boots shiny, but Zone forbid you confuse him with a rookie. I took one like that by mistake once, spent two weeks scrubbing my lair with a toothbrush, barely escaped. He's called 'Comrade Sergeant Major'."</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_59"><text>Listen to this new joke, they told it in the bar. A stalker comes to Sidorovich one day. And Sidorovich says to him:\n- Listen, stalker. I got a spacesuit from some secret Kyiv research institute, supposedly with one hundred percent protection from radiation. Only nobody has tested it yet. Go into the Zone wearing it, see what's what. Then I'll give you a discount on it, if you survive... The stalker agreed. Went into the Zone, and one day passes, then two, then three... On the fourth day he comes back, mean as a Snork, and slams the spacesuit onto Sidorovich's table without a word. Sidorovich is stunned:\n- What is it, stalker? Doesn't protect you? \n- It protects me! \n- Not one hundred percent? \n- One hundred percent!\n- Then what are you unhappy about? \n- The whole Zone treats radiation with vodka from morning till night, and I ALONE, LIKE AN IDIOT, AM SOBER FOR THE FOURTH DAY!!!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_60"><text>I saw Monolith members clearing the territory near the Scorcher the other day, about thirty men, killing anything that moved: Fleshes, Boars, even "trampling" dogs... So I, well... got out of there fast, just in case. I don't feel like catching lead in the ass.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_61"><text>Want to hear a joke? A "Нива [TERM?]" is tearing down the road toward the pre-Zone area, doing about 120 kilometers an hour. A traffic cop is blowing his whistle like a songbird, the "Нива [TERM?]" brakes, a whole squad of Duty boys climbs out, beats the soldier's ass, shoves the whistle up his ass, and races on. The traffic cop grabs his radio:\n- Seven two-seven three!\n- Seven two!\n- Сеня [TERM?]! Some bastard is flying your way and won't react to the whistle! So stop him with the baton, the baton! Do you copy, seven-two?..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_62"><text>Man, have you ever heard of Фантом [TERM?], no? I'll tell you, you won't believe it. They say there was once a stalker in the Zone, don't know his name, everyone called him Фантом [TERM?]. He was experienced, and a good man too, understood people and they understood him. People said he studied psychology at an institute. Doesn't matter, though, getting to the main thing: he was slippery, could slip anywhere, checkpoints and anomalies weren't obstacles to him. He went deep into the Zone, then one day vanished, most likely got caught in an emission or something. Anyway, he became something like a poltergeist. For ten years now he's been walking the Zone, looking for other stalkers. When he finds you, he looks into your soul. If you're a good person, he'll help somehow: lead you to shelter, help you fight off mutants. But if you've got more sins than you can count, buddy, hide yourself, because he'll tear you to pieces. There's your bedtime story...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_63"><text>Marked One, where did you get a gun like that? Bought it from Sidorovich, I bet? Yeah, his guns are nice, but they cost way too much. The bastard probably buys them from the army for pennies and sells them to us at triple price! No thanks, buddy, I wasn't born stupid. I'd rather look for a gun at Garbage. Sure, it might glow so hard you start glowing too, but at least it's free.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_64"><text>Listen, stalker, somebody told me a good one the other day. Here it is. Duty members and Freedom stalkers are having it out. So the Freedom commander stands up and shouts:\n- Forward, for Freedom! - and everyone charges, you understand. Duty stalkers on the other side of the front:\n- That's it, we're screwed, time to run.\nAnd an old, experienced Duty man says:\n- Wait before you run, - pulls out a machine gun: tra-ta-ta-ta. The Freedomers drop. Five minutes pass, a Freedomer stands up again:\n- For the Zone! Hurra-a-a-a-a-ah! - and they all charge again. Duty:\n- Now we're definitely screwed, time to run.\nThe old Duty man:\n- Wait! - grabs a Kalash and does his "tra-ta-ta-ta" again. So the Freedomers drop again. Some more time passes. The Freedom commander stands up again:\n- For our boys, for Freedom in the Zone, forward! - and they charge again. Duty's young ones panic again. The old Duty man does his thing again. Freedom has to lie down again. Five minutes later the Freedom commander stands up. Face in shit, covered in shit, and roars: \n- Fuck, I don't get it!\nThe old Duty man, flicking his cigarette aside: \n- Now it's time to run.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_65"><text>Heard about the mercenaries? No? Then listen carefully and take notes: they're killers, buddy. Serious, desperate men too. They'll get anyone you want, alive or dead. Remember Сыч [TERM?], who got whacked recently? Precise shot to the heart and head, body burned, no traces at the scene. Their work, believe me. Those bastards have no conscience. Killing a man is no different to them than crushing a cockroach; they only respect coin. Rumor says they have a base in Мёртвый город [TERM?], but nobody has ever come back alive from there. They don't like strangers. And do you know how they train? They catch some bandit or stalker, bring him to their place, give him a Kalash with two magazines, and let him go in any direction. If the man isn't dead after 12 hours, he can keep living. That's their idea of fun, buddy. In all that time only Миша Косой [TERM?] managed to stay alive, and only because he served ten years in special forces. So, Marked One, if you see guys in blue suits, put your legs to work and run far away. Though if they've already set their eye on you, you won't get away anyway. They'll dig you out from underground.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_66"><text>They say there's one group of people... Sometimes they're called shamans, sometimes druids. They say they don't carry any electronic equipment at all, closer to nature and all that... Well, they say the Zone reacts more strongly to electronics, to all kinds of electromagnetic emissions... and sets monsters on you too. The way they see it, the Zone is a living organism. You can't go poking into it with devices, they say; a proper person can manage without any extra attachments. Though the bastards do carry assault rifles... Why not try teeth and claws, then... On the other hand, it seems not that many of them die in the Zone. No more often than us, anyway... So maybe they figured something out right... They mostly come into the Zone from the Беларусь [TERM?] side, though... Would be nice to get a look at them... And check how many artifacts they have in their pockets while we're at it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_67"><text>Listen, Barkeep told me Bloodsuckers attacked the village near the Army Warehouses yesterday. Nobody got out alive, they didn't even manage to send a proper signal. Duty members went to check the next day. They say it was a slaughterhouse in there, boys cut up like pigs, scraps lying everywhere... horror, basically.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_68"><text>Got a cigarette? You don't smoke? Clear enough... Right thing to do, by the way. Good for the body, and keeps your lungs ready for running from dogs, heh-heh... Anyway, you know, some skilled mercenaries, damned snipers, used to drop stalkers in the dark by an interesting principle. When stalkers gathered in a group and relaxed with nicotine, the mercenary would spot the flare of the match and the cigarette glow when the first man lit up. Then, when the second stalker lit his cigarette, the match flame moved, the second smoke lit, and the sniper led the transfer of fire. The third lit up and immediately got a bullet in the head... That's why stalkers now have a rule: "Three do not light from one match." So jokes are jokes, but a man's life can depend on little things like that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_69"><text>I ran into some dazed man here. He had an army suit, a special-forces rifle, and behaved like a pure zombie: one leg half dragging, movements unclear, body barely obeying him... I almost shot him at first. What stopped me was that he kept a tight grip on his rifle. I've seen plenty of zombies in my time, but never one like that. He was trying to tell me something too, only I barely made anything out... Only understood "Controller" and "help." I was just about to help the kid when I heard a chopper, got scared, and ran. Dove into a little grove. Seven soldiers appeared, then the helicopter. Three kept the kid in their sights, and the others rushed him and threw him to the ground. Imagine that, their own man, face in the mud! They were shouting something about some helmet. Then they dragged him under the arms into the helicopter... Something strange here... That kid, his words about the Controller... the soldiers... Did he really manage to get away from a Controller...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_70"><text>I recently managed to sit by the campfire with a mercenary. Turned out he wasn't a bad guy. He killed stalkers, as you understand, only on orders from his bosses, never just because. In general, mercenaries treat our stalker kind pretty well, especially experienced men and veterans. They respect us, though they consider only themselves unsurpassed masters. And that mercenary told me the story of his life. For his service, he has an Order of Courage and a Medal for Bravery. He studied at a sniper training center. Everything there was serious: weapon checks every time, and so on. But he said this: real sniper skills can only be acquired in war, in hot zones. Sometimes a man would be trained long and thoroughly, but once it came time for the exam, usually held in Чечня [TERM?], no, he couldn't do it, and that was that. In school you can prepare, shoot targets, hit them confidently, but at the most important moment something can switch on inside a person, and he simply can't do it. That's how it is. So you, Marked One, be more confident in the Zone. If something threatens your life, be confident. Psychology.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_71"><text>I'll tell you this: I got into a terrible scrape and barely crawled out. I was walking along, and suddenly bang! Everything around me went dark, horrible sound, like something was eating you, I almost had all my veins opened. Somehow I dumped some of my junk and crawled out. Luck actually helped: my sack was worn out, the strap snapped under the strain and pulled the fabric, opening a hole. Something fell out, and that's how I was saved. Fate! Good thing I had bandages with me. Took me a week to recover after that blood loss. That's some nasty shit. God forbid you get caught in it!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_72"><text>Have you heard about the tricky anomaly? Let me tell you, it's a real piece of filth! You can barely see it, like some black puddle, but if you fall in, you'll know right away. And Zone help you if you hesitate: shake something out of your backpack fast, and don't even think about what you need and what you don't. Anything, as long as you get out, or you won't have time. It'll eat you alive, I'm telling you straight, saw it myself. Thank God it didn't happen to me, but the boys explained afterward what that shit was.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_73"><text>Heard how one stalker got into "Проглотка [TERM?]"? Well, stalkers also call it "Жадинка [TERM?]," different people, different names... What, you've never heard of one at all? Then listen: there is such an anomaly, not common, but if you meet it, God help you if you step in... So this stalker was coming from somewhere loaded with good loot. And he was an experienced man, too, but somehow it happened... fatigue probably got him. I don't know what he went through in there; you can't stay in it for more than a minute, it'll eat you like nothing. But for him that minute must have felt like eternity. Crawled out barely alive, bleeding all over, suit in shreds, loot gone... Lucky he lived, and the boys nearby supplied him with bandages. He could have kept his loot, too. Why did it happen? Greed. He carried a lot and didn't want to throw anything away, so he hesitated, thinking. In a business like that, you can't think long. So my advice to you, God forbid, of course: if you get caught, throw whatever comes to hand and run for it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_74"><text>Do you already know anything about anomalies? "Vortex," "Springboard," that sort... heard of them? Well, I'll tell you: all that is nothing compared to "Чёртова глотка [TERM?]," or "Жадинка [TERM?]" - they're the same thing. Why? Because if you fall into another anomaly, everything is clear: either you get out or you don't... If you get out, you're alive and your loot is with you, lucky, in short. Knock on wood... But if you land in this one, there's only one way out: throw something to it so it calms down, and crawl out at once. And that's the whole nasty part. Any stalker will hold out until the last second rather than part with his loot. But this is exactly the kind of case where you can't hold out under any circumstances. Hold out too long, and you'll be stretched out dead... Nice way I said that. But that's how it is. Remember it, it'll come in handy.
</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_75"><text>I sometimes ask myself: why the hell do we keep running around like this? To earn money? But what the hell do we need money for if all we do is keep running around?..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_76"><text>They showed me a new cocktail in the Bar, called "Witch's Jelly." It's the kind of thing, buddy, that's dangerous to take on an empty stomach: one serving and your arms and legs stop working...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_77"><text>I sometimes ask myself: why the hell do we keep running around like this? To earn money? But what the hell do we need money for if all we do is keep running around?..</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_78"><text>One rookie was always afraid to stick his nose past the Cordon. Garbage? Dark Valley? No way, are you kidding, monsters and bandits out there... But he still wanted to get something. How do you find anything sitting in one place? Someone told him, go to Санаторий [TERM?]... that's what one local area is called... it's quiet there, nobody around, and you'll fill up with loot. Stalkers don't usually go to this Санаторий [TERM?], because there's been nothing useful there for a long time. They were just messing with him. \nSo he took two sacks, got directions from someone, and trudged off. One day gone, two days gone... he only showed up a week later! Turns out he met either some bloodsucker thing or a Burer there, says he barely survived and had to lie low... Probably lying, raising his own price or making excuses because he came back empty. Why make excuses? It was obvious there was nothing to catch there, and the fool fell for it. I haven't been there myself, and I don't feel like wearing out my legs for nothing, so I never even learned the way.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_79"><text>I heard bandits are roaming somewhere around here on the Cordon. What do they need here? One man said they can get from the Cordon to Санаторий [TERM?]. Know anything about that? And from there, maybe somewhere else. I'd like to go see what's so special about this Санаторий [TERM?], just need to find the path... Somebody definitely knows, but that's how it is with us: they find a route and keep quiet like partisans, and if they do say something, it won't be for free.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_80"><text>Heard there was a path to Санаторий [TERM?] somewhere around here? No? And I was just about to ask you... Well, fine, maybe someone knows.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_81"><text>I don't know, I'm very new here myself. Nothing special so far.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_82"><text>I saw a Bloodsucker from a distance three days ago. Well, I mean, they told me it was a Bloodsucker. I looked through binoculars; it looked like a soldier. Is it true they look human? I'm starting to doubt it was a Bloodsucker. Maybe they played me...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_83"><text>I went to the ATP the other day, thought nobody was there. I walk up to the gate and hear some mumbling. I listened closer, and they're talking criminal slang in there. So I thought, to hell with walks like that. I've got a "Макар [TERM?]" under my jacket and cartridges too, but better to keep myself safe. So I turned around and ran back here. Told the men not to poke their noses in for now. You don't go either, wait a while.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_84"><text>Do you have a radiation counter yet? Don't forget to hang it on your belt, or you can step in it badly. I went nearby here once, forgot about the counter at first. Came back, felt awful, the men pointed a device at me, and it started cracking! Everyone shouted: "Take your clothes off, fool!" And I felt sorry for them, the suit was almost new. In the end they stripped me naked by force and threw everything far down into a ravine. Found me some bits of clothing. Then everyone drank vodka to recover, and they made me drink too. My head buzzed for two days. Turns out where I went, there was radioactive dust everywhere. If I hadn't forgotten the counter, I wouldn't be walking around in these rags now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_85"><text>Last week rain poured for three... no, four days straight. And right nearby, not far from here, there wasn't a drop. They say even the weather has turned anomalous in this Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_86"><text>Boars sometimes run into the village here. So the day before yesterday I was sleeping, heard shooting, thought soldiers had come, was about to jump into the cellar. Looked out, and the boys were chasing Boars. There you go... Be careful, even at the base.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_87"><text>There's an anomaly that can throw you across a distance. I went past the bridge here, walked around a bit, tossed bolts. And that bastard doesn't show up with bolts. I thought, right here it's clear, I'll pass through, and after that the path is already worn in. Then I flew somewhere, went blind at first, then forced my eyes open, holy shit, I'm on some rocks somewhere, and Boars are digging the ground with their snouts all around. Well, I figured out I wasn't far from the base, so I sat quietly for half an hour, waited until they left, then ran from there. That's how it goes in the Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_88"><text>At night there was howling across the whole area. I jumped right up. They say: dogs, don't be scared. And I thought all the dead had risen at once and started screaming, it was that awful. What kind of dogs are those...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_89"><text>During the last emission, I felt so bad, so sick in my soul... This is the third emission I've watched, and every time it gets worse and worse. Maybe it accumulates in a person like radiation, huh? You don't know... I asked the boys, nobody knows.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_90"><text>They told me yesterday: the boys killed a Boar nearby and wanted to cook it. They wonder where to roast it, nobody had matches to start a fire, and they were too lazy to go anywhere far. One of them suggested: "Let's put it near the Burner and throw bolts so it cooks, and we'll turn it over from time to time." So that's what they did. Only the fools don't understand: that's an ANOMALY! Not just a big campfire. How it roasts there, nobody knows. Maybe weak once, strong the next... hell if you can understand it. Five minutes hadn't passed, and the little Boar was nothing but charcoal. That's what you call dinner.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_91"><text>The other day I found an interesting thing near an anomaly. Looked like a gemstone. I showed it to our people, and they were all surprised. Looks exactly like an emerald, they said. In nature, all those stones are found at the sites of old cataclysms too. I mean places where thousands of years ago there was high temperature and pressure... So I thought, maybe here you can collect stones and sell them as precious gems too. There are places like that here. Some kind of loot either way... Need to talk to the traders.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_92"><text>I was coming back from a run, a little tired, got distracted, and caught the edge of an Electro. It slammed me hard! Weapon out of my hands, and I flew off, luckily to the side and not into the center of the anomaly. I came to and saw my "Винторез [TERM?]" lying there, nothing happened to it, but there's no way to reach it. Now I go there three times a day, checking whether it's still there. Waiting for the anomaly to dissipate, since they do change places sometimes. The gun is brand new, I paid so much loot for it... If not for that, would I be standing guard over an anomaly?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_93"><text>We've got one man who deliberately throws different things into anomalies and watches what happens to them. So the other day he threw a grenade into either a Springboard or a Vortex, and it got tossed up, spun around, and torn to pieces. It went off like ten grenades at once. Hell knows, maybe it was some special Vortex, charged up. Everyone grabbed their guns at once, jumped up, thought an emission had hit. We calmed down more or less, and then he came back and told us what he'd done... Fool, in short. Well, no problem, now he won't throw anything for about a week, until the bruises go down. He sees badly out of both eyes now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_94"><text>Nothing new... Sitting here, sipping vodka while there is some. Well, dogs were running nearby, so we shot them out of boredom. Otherwise, nothing new...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_95"><text>The other day one stalker came back with a lot of loot. Of course he didn't keep it on him, experienced man, hid it in a reliable place. But that's not the point. The point is, people tell the truth: there are anomalous fields that artifacts just love. It's like mushrooms, you understand? In a birch grove you find brown caps, in a pine forest porcini. Lots at once, same here. So it's still worth walking around and looking. Not everything has been picked clean yet...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_96"><text>I'll tell you this: I ran into a Bloodsucker the other day. Nothing new, you always need to be ready for that, especially keep a good shotgun at hand. And as luck would have it, I wasn't ready. I only had an AK and not that many rounds... I went almost light, thought I had piles of ammo in my stash and a shotgun too, why drag extra weight for nothing. Didn't make it. I hear someone huffing. I listened closer, familiar kind of huffing, but nobody visible. I had just cocked the AK when it attacked from behind, knocked the weapon out of my hands, and appeared in all its beauty. I was standing nose to nose with it. My instinct kicked in right away: knife to the throat! Made it. If I'd hesitated a couple seconds, I'd be finished. So a gun is a gun, but always keep a knife ready.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_97"><text>I left supplies in one noticeable place. Came there the other day, and everything was gone, cleaned out completely. Bastards, there really are assholes in this world! If it had been bandits, fine, what do you expect from them, crooks are crooks. But it was our own stalkers who took it, surely. No, assholes like that won't last long in the Zone. I'll kill them myself if I see my own stuff.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_98"><text>I recently shot all kinds of wildlife: Boars, dogs, even winged a Chimera. And I didn't count the Tushkanos at all. Collected all kinds of limbs from them, the ones that were whole or usable, and sold everything to the trader. Came out pretty well. You could basically stop collecting loot and just work monsters, if you have hunting skill. And I do.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_99"><text>Last week a Pseudogiant dragged itself here, and we barely put it down. We had to fuss with it, but all the men were experienced. They climbed higher and pelted it with grenades. Nobody got hurt. With one of those, the main thing is finding a place higher and more reliable, meaning more stable. A big boulder or something like that. God forbid you're standing nearby on the ground when it slaps you with a paw; it'll shake all your guts out at once. Effect is like a head-on car crash... Listen to veterans' stories and take notes.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_100"><text>We went to see the soldiers recently. Turns out you can stock up nicely on ammo and other things from them if you approach them with a business proposal. And they have one need, which means only one offer... guess on the first try what they need, ha-ha.</text></string>

<string id="dm_cool_info_101"><text>We were sitting quiet, drinking, singing, having a bite... Then some creep barged in and started throwing his weight around. Well, that was the end of his weight-throwing... Idiot. If he had talked like a human being, fine, but why start flexing right away... who is he to show off in front of us?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_102"><text>Duty members have lost their damn minds, seriously. They keep pushing into the Dark Valley. Who invited them here? Just the other day another smartass showed up... No problem, let him think a little about sticking his nose in without an invitation.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_103"><text>I checked a buddy's stash recently. He left it to me... heh-heh. Must have been storing food for winter or something, there was a mountain of it, the damn Jew. And I kept wondering why he always had new gear. Turns out he was selling food and buying himself kit. Fine by me, now I'll make a profit off his chow.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_104"><text>We were drinking here with the whole crew, and as usual some fool showed up - the turd at the party - and got in Бритый [TERM?]'s face. They locked horns, grabbed their guns, but the men told them right away: want a showdown, fine... knives only, and we'll stand in a circle and watch, no need to ruin our evening... Well, Бритый [TERM?] dropped him, of course, no question. Бритый [TERM?] is a hardened man, and that one was just a kid, I do not even remember his handle. A greenhorn, in short. The piss just went to his head; he sure picked the wrong man to push.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_105"><text>I blew everything at twenty-one... Fuck, what do I do now? No weapon, no ammo - pissed it all away. You can't go into the Zone in just long johns. What an idiot I am...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_106"><text>Nothing special in the news. Chased some mutants around, put down one bandit... Same as always.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_107"><text>Soon they'll shut down this whole racket, I mean the trade in various artifacts. That's the word going around... And good, long overdue. They opened up trade here, spread this contagion around, and the Zone keeps crawling outward.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_108"><text>We're organizing a new recruitment drive. Mostly focused on rookie stalkers, the ones the Zone hasn't ruined too badly yet. Want to serve Duty? Then run to the Bar and sign up.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_109"><text>All the main news is in the Bar, go there. While you're at it, take on some work too; better for the common cause than drifting around and picking up junk all over the Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_110"><text>I don't know, I just got back from a raid. Haven't heard any news yet...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_111"><text>The other day someone wandered in from the Warehouses side. We thought he was just a stalker. But he lingered, asked what was what, where we kept weapons, how many of us were here... The men figured out what kind of bird he was right away. Found himself some fools, the damned anarchist, like we'd tell him everything. He doesn't ask anymore.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_112"><text>There was this case: we were sitting by the campfire at night, all starting to nod off. Suddenly something slapped down nearby, nobody understood at first. Then a canister flew into the wall, and someone's weapon got knocked out of his hands. That's when we realized a Burer had shown up. We scattered fast into position, thought he was about to come for us. Then we looked, and dogs were chasing him across the field. Poor bastard was running from them, barely dodging - a whole pack was after him, and strips were already hanging off him. All he did was throw stones and random junk at them. We even felt sorry for that Burer. But we watched the circus and everyone woke right up.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_113"><text>What news is there, no TV, no radio. Everyone makes something up and serves it as the news of the day... Boring as hell.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_114"><text>"We sat and drank whatever came - Madeira, Starka, St. John's wort..." Know that song? Same with us. That's the news we have, and there isn't any other.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_115"><text>One fool lost his fancy gun while drunk. So we hid it first, then tossed it farther out onto the minefield to see what he would do. He kept walking around whining: where is it, where is it. So we told him: you wandered onto the minefield yourself and left it there, and we pointed out the gun to him... So off he went. The whole base watched his clown show through binoculars, crawling on all fours and probing the ground with a cleaning rod. Some sapper, ha-ha.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_116"><text>One man decided to prank me, told me about a stash like I would take the bait. I know those jokes. I agreed, then offered it to one rookie instead. So I watched from a hill through my scope as he searched that stash, crawling to it on all fours. It was mined, well, not for real, just a smoke popper. Oh, how he jumped and squealed... we had a good laugh.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_117"><text>Mutants came pushing in from the Барьер [TERM?] side, and we barely stopped them. Where do they come from over there? Maybe someone breeds them on purpose, haven't heard?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_118"><text>We had a newcomer show up recently. So we laughed at him a little. He got wiped out hard from not being used to it - who drinks that much right away with no food - and at night one man gave him a whole set of hickeys. We have a fellow here who likes that kind of thing. In the morning we started telling him how he got drunk and went to the Bloodsucker village, chasing them around and yelling: "Come on out, we're going to fight!" Then we pointed at the hickeys. The kid almost shit himself... And we had a laugh.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_119"><text>Duty members dropped by, thought we just drink here and could be taken barehanded. Like hell! Sure, we were a little drunk, but for me that only helps - steadier hand and sharper eye, if you keep it moderate. Dropped two of them, and the rest ran back to the Bar quick. No need to stick their noses in here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_120"><text>I saw one kid's gun. The grip was done up with some kind of plexiglass, and under it was an oil painting or something like that. Pretty, but what the hell is it for... To me the main thing is that it shoots straight. Decorating it like that is just showing off.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_cool_info_121"><text>We found a door here, well, an entrance somewhere, hell knows where. We tried forcing it and forcing it, nothing. Welded shut, maybe, or locked from the other side... Maybe that's where those creeps from Duty come from? Too many of them around here...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_cool_info_122"><text>One man here lost everything at dice and now he whines: give me this, give me that... Why the hell was he playing high stakes with someone else's dice? Fool. If you're betting big, you need your own dice. A lesson for a sucker like him...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_cool_info_123"><text>The other day we caught a stalker with loot on him. What a sap, carrying it all with him... So he started whining: I'll give it all up, just let me go. Sure you'll give it up, and you'll work it off too if you want to live. So he did a little mule work for us: we gave him a basic gun and sent him where we needed. Worked out fine - he shot some doggies, some Tushkanos. We kept him in our sights, of course, so he only pointed the gun the right way. He cleared the area for us, though not all of it... didn't give him many rounds, heh-heh. And to hell with him, plenty of fools still walking around.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_cool_info_124"><text>The boss has been in a bad mood lately. I went to him, and he tore me up good... What's got into him?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_125"><text>Nothing new, same work as always.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_126"><text>Who are you that I should tell you the news? Keep walking.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_127"><text>No news, and even if there was, you wouldn't hear it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_128"><text>We don't like chatter here. And we don't like people who ask too many questions.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_129"><text>If we're still tolerating you here, that doesn't mean you can do whatever you want. Don't ask too much. Better yet, walk around silent.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_130"><text>You're still alive. That's news already...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_131"><text>What news? Open your mouth less, especially here. Walk while you still can, just keep quiet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_132"><text>You're still here? Haven't gathered all the news yet? Come on, get out of here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_133"><text>Can you play dice? Come on, stop acting like a good little boy. You probably already played at the Bar with Baldy... So I'll tell you this: don't deal with him, he's one hell of a bastard. Recently he cleaned out Пашка [TERM?] so badly everyone stood there with their mouths open - how can the same number come up three times in a row? And the man had just come back from a raid. Found something valuable, naturally... He had a lot of loot, too. I warned him the same way: don't deal with Baldy. But no... And now what? He walks around the Bar like the last bum, and he had that much loot! Ah. Fool.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_134"><text>Yesterday at the Bar I lost twenty grand to Baldy. Didn't play anymore after that... Something about his luck smells wrong. And tell me... you look like a stalker, sort of... where does he get artifacts he can put on the table so casually? He sits in the Bar, never goes anywhere... So where from? Nobody knows.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_135"><text>Sometimes people play in the Bar here. Haven't tried it yet? You put down money - he answers with an artifact. Then it depends how the die turns, meaning what number comes up. The rules aren't hard, only the whole thing is strange... I think Baldy - he's the man who stakes artifacts - is somehow in cahoots with Barkeep. Because Barkeep buys arts cheap from rookies. He sees your face looks like a rookie's, and that's it, consider yourself skinned clean. Then he somehow rents those artifacts to Baldy, Baldy makes his profit and pays Barkeep back in money. That's what we talked over among ourselves and decided. Otherwise it doesn't add up, Baldy having both money and arts.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_136"><text>They beat me again in the Bar. Those fuckers... They're doing something crooked with the bets there. Fine, we'll still tune up Baldy's face...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_137"><text>Ah... I'm an idiot. They warned me, didn't they: don't stake arts, stake money. I pissed it all away. And if I had sold them, imagine where I'd be now. I had almost a hundred grand there, no less... What an idiot.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_138"><text>Get lost! Demob is right around the corner... and after that! I'll live properly...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_139"><text>Move along... Know too much, and no one will ever find you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_140"><text>You should be more careful... nearby, at the pumping station, some brave little officer set up a secret little oil refinery, picked soldiers as guards - real cutthroats, and their faces... compared to them, mutants are cartoon animals. I'm afraid they might do something stupid while drunk. So keep an eye out.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_141"><text>My colleagues and I decided to set up a bathhouse at the former boat station. After dissecting certain representatives of the local fauna, you get so saturated with the smell that I fear some stalkers may soon start shooting at our kind in the dark. </text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_142"><text>Most curious people turn up, I must say. Yesterday they brought in one such case... he had two molecules of life left in him, but he kept asking about some album of drawings and tugging at the amulet on his chest... We thought he would die, even wanted to call Father Diodor, but when we woke up in the morning, he was gone without a trace... Miracles...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_143"><text>You go on your way. I don't know anything...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_144"><text>I don't know. Seems like nothing. Ask around, maybe someone will tell you something.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_145"><text>What could be new in the Zone, think about it yourself? Same monsters, same anomalies, same faces every day.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_146"><text>I learned one tricky little recipe. Tried it, and it worked. Turns out it's all so simple, while at first I couldn't figure out what was what at all.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_147"><text>Where would we get news? We sit here on the edge of nowhere. If someone tells us something from somewhere, we're the last to hear it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_148"><text>I don't know anything. Some people go far, then tell all kinds of interesting stories, and I just sit here and listen. They tell me: why are you sitting here, at least go to Garbage. I'll get there. The slower you go, the farther you'll get.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_149"><text>There was an incident the other day: bandit scum came pouring in by the line. Where did so many of them come from? And they push in brazenly, don't give a damn about anything. They don't even care whether they live or die. What kind of people are they! We fought them off in the end, but it's a shame about our boys. They were good men.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_150"><text>As usual, one of the stalkers ended up in an anomaly. How many times have people said it: you can't run around the Zone without a head on your shoulders. First probe the path with a bolt, then go. But no! Always in a hurry... never enough time for them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_151"><text>Well, want me to tell you a few words about the Burer? Have you even seen one? When you do, you'll know right away it's him. Your head starts humming and all kinds of objects start flying. And God forbid you meet his eyes! The moment you spot him from a distance, hide. If he sees you, he'll suck your whole soul out through his stare.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_152"><text>Know about Bloodsuckers? When you're walking anywhere, always listen. That's how you have to move everywhere in the Zone. You have to listen to the Zone. So, as soon as you sense someone huffing nearby - even a hint of huffing - that's it! Run, or you won't make it. Well, if you're tough and carrying a huge gun, you can face him. Only he's such a bastard, he can come from behind, you won't even notice, and then no gun will help you. Better to run right away.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_153"><text>I know now how to deal with Snorks. Truth is, I haven't run into one yet, thank God. But experienced stalkers told me: you can sense a Snork right away, it's too noisy. The noise gives it away. As soon as you hear that kind of... guttural sound, maybe, it means he's nearby. Best aim for the head. And the main thing is don't gape, the bastard is very quick. If he jumps at you, move aside at once and shoot. Better yet, hit him in midair, but still move aside right away, then finish him. That's theory, of course. I haven't had practice myself yet, but it is still better to know what to do in advance.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_154"><text>I recently went out on some business, and those... little ones attacked me. Tushkanos. What nasty things! Like locusts. They'll gnaw anyone to death, small as they look. With them, the main thing is to jump onto something high right away - a rock, a car, a fallen tree. And while they swarm around down below, calmly pick them off with a pistol. Only you need to aim carefully, because they're so quick you can spend your whole supply and still not hit a single one.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_155"><text>One stalker said people had seen dogs that weren't really real, like an illusion. Supposedly something like a Pseudodog runs at you, you shoot, and it disappears, then runs again. What the hell is that? True, or are they lying? In the Zone, anything can happen...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_156"><text>They say the rats running around here sometimes are mutating too. Someone saw not a rat, but a damn giant rat! Like a dog. And they also say rats attacked one stalker and ate him alive, while the second barely got away. He told the story afterward. Terrible things are happening.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_157"><text>Dogs ate one stalker recently. He kept bragging: I can do this, I have that! Said he had an assault rifle, and they were just brainless dogs. So he bragged himself into trouble - ran into such a pack he didn't even have time to change magazines. Exactly, they're brainless, they don't understand they're being shot. And while you're shooting one, ten more are already chewing your legs... Braggarts like that don't live long in the Zone.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_158"><text>Something happened with the army boys at Agroprom. They say helicopters were flying, looked like some bigwig came in... for an inspection. Probably someone stole something as usual, or they lost something, who knows... Just in case: don't show yourself there too much, that's my advice.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_159"><text>People are saying the military started stirring at Agroprom... I don't really care, but they say there was some kind of mess there. Or maybe just a rotation... or whatever they call it, one group gets taken out, another brought in, and all the fuss comes from that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_160"><text>I heard the army boys don't stand on ceremony with stalkers much anymore. Rumor says some clever bastard got into their Agroprom base... though I honestly didn't understand where, the base itself or the database. Not the point... something went missing from them, in short. An acquaintance told me that, and a soldier whispered it to him, warned him, basically, so our stalkers would watch themselves around there for a while.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_161"><text>The army boys have some kind of reinforcements here on the Cordon. And a man from Agroprom dropped by too, said it's the same there. They're planning something, or maybe someone ran off... or got killed... Just guesses. We're sitting here wondering what brought it on. So be even more careful with them now, because who knows what's on their minds and what new orders they've received...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_162"><text>Agroprom has been restless lately for some reason. I'm sitting here and not going out for now. I almost stuck my nose out, wanted to crawl to the Cordon, then heard some serious shooting. Something is clearly happening. I think I'll sit it out here until everything calms down. I only just got back on my feet, and now to catch a bullet... why would I need that kind of joy.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_163"><text>You went to the Dark Valley, didn't you... Better tell me yourself what they're saying there. One stalker said some fool either got into a sealed laboratory or was about to. He lied, of course... who would risk that? And if it's true, I wouldn't want to be in his place. Once, back when the entrance was almost open, our people tried to poke in there and barely got out alive - so much wildlife in there. If you learn anything, tell me...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_164"><text>Seems they brought Barkeep something unusual. A guard heard Barkeep talking with some smart types, something about technical documentation, some laboratory... What could he even be saying there? He's no technician. What does he know about documentation... But I'd be interested in looking through those docs myself.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_165"><text>Stalkers wounded one bandit. So, to get them to let him go, he started telling fairy tales about a cache in a laboratory nearby. Not up top either, but down below, in the laboratory itself, imagine that. They told him: what are you feeding us, there's no way in there! But he swore someone found a key and even went there. Haven't heard anything? The cache is bullshit, of course, but could there really be a passage now?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_166"><text>There was a stalker from the Dark Valley here right before you, started talking all kinds of nonsense about an underground laboratory. I don't know why stalkers suddenly got interested in laboratories again... Those laboratories really do exist. I remember back when the Clear Sky group was working, there was a lot of talk about them. There were different plans for them, but only the leadership knew what, how, and why. Then everyone went quiet, and now there's suddenly some real excitement again.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_167"><text>What news would we have here, just echoes of gossip. A stalker came by recently and spun such a tale: supposedly they found a key to some underground laboratory and someone even went there... True, he didn't say whether the man came back. And it was obvious anyway: of course he didn't come back, otherwise why would he be telling it? Clear enough he made it up himself. I say all that is stalker folklore. Laboratories are to stalkers what castle dungeons are, with their secrets and dead men guarding those secrets. That's why I say nobody could have come back, otherwise he'd come out and say: it's all fairy tales, boys, don't believe any of it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_168"><text>I heard a rumor that some underground place was opened somewhere. And supposedly everything there died out... or everyone died out... and you can find a lot of interesting things. Worth believing, what do you think? If everything and everyone died out, what's so interesting there? Though... some junk probably stayed behind.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_169"><text>I recently went out to the stalkers to get some food, and they told me monsters came crawling out of some underground levels... supposedly some idiot blew open a door down there. Look at what is happening! And I'm sitting here and know nothing...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_170"><text>Now we have a group at Yantar too, guarding the scientists. Why guard them, they're in a bunker... we'd better survive ourselves. Do you know how much filth is there! Dead men walking like they're alive. They say someone opened some lower levels there... I don't know properly, but it is certain that all kinds of filth crawled out of there. You haven't been there by chance? Seen those dead men? If you go, help our boys; they say they're having a rough time there now, not like here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_171"><text>They say things are lively at Yantar. Duty even assigned some of their own people there. One man came here to get repaired after duty, said he nearly went gray there. Shot so much his barrel could have melted. He didn't stop until he spent all his ammo; they barely calmed him down. And it all started recently, after someone went into the territory of that... uh... X-lab. Looks like he stirred up those creatures, and they came in a wave. But that's just my guess. Ask around at Yantar about what's what.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_172"><text>Duty has another problem now: Yantar. One Duty member came by recruiting for their ranks. Started talking pretty about defending humanity, this and that... But once he drank, his tongue loosened. He said they actually don't have enough people, and now there is duty at Yantar too. Mostly volunteers get sent there, but there aren't many takers. Someone opened either a hatch or a passage there... and the monsters that had been locked up sort of smelled freedom, then all rushed outside. So that's why nobody is eager to go there: it's become very dangerous.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_173"><text>I heard a rumor that someone really did visit the laboratories after all... at Yantar, maybe, or somewhere there. I doubt it's true, because even in our time everything was sealed tight there and all the passages were blocked. Though if someone really wants in, he'll find a way. Anything can happen. Fanat recently asked someone to go to a laboratory specifically for some documents, and he offered it to me too... Actually, he's the one who told me about it. Only nobody agreed. We aren't suicides here, and I don't need it that badly.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_174"><text>What news do we have? We ask everyone ourselves. The other day someone came to Сергеич [TERM?], seemed to be from the scientists at Yantar. I was just bringing them food. They were mumbling something about their research, fluc... what do you call it... tuations or something, and then I hear Сергеич [TERM?] get surprised by something. Laboratory, he says, radiation? Can't be, he says, for it to be turned off, just the power, he says, is variable... At that point I stopped understanding anything and left, so I wouldn't clog my head with it. So what was that about? You don't know either... shame.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_175"><text>Rumor has it there will soon be a major scrap between the Duty grunts and Freedom. Freedom, supposedly, had its eye on the passage to Yantar, so the Duty grunts hurried up and they're already there. One man was coming from the Bar and told me. He says the Duty grunts deliberately released zombies from some underground levels at Yantar so that, if it came to it, Freedom would waste all its strength on them. Like some kind of barrier. Only a "barrier" like that can come back to bite them. You can't stuff ideals into zombies' heads; they don't care who they kill.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_176"><text>I don't know anything. I feel more or less all right now, need to get to the Bar. At least they'll tell me something there. Otherwise, everyone who comes by tells how dead men from the complex at Yantar moved out in a crowd. That was after Duty members made a raid there. Seems that way... You don't know what to believe, I need to go to the Bar myself and ask around.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_177"><text>People here say Duty members are getting stronger. They've gotten completely brazen, want to grab everything for themselves. Something happened at Yantar - someone switched something on or off, hell if you can understand... so under that cover they quickly found both funds and men and already dug in there. And now they think it's their lawful territory. Same thing happened in the Dark Valley. Someone went somewhere there, let somebody out of a cage, and there they were at once, starting to "protect" all humanity from the spawn of the Zone. They probably encouraged it themselves so they'd have a "legal" excuse for a takeover. Fine... let them have their fun. We won't let them in here, and we won't let them pass farther either.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_178"><text>I was just about to ask you... Someone told me mutants came in a wave, not here, but in the Dark Valley, and at Yantar too. They blew something up there, I think... a passage or an exit, I don't really know. What I do know is that we may get more work now: shooting monsters, if that wave rolls this far.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_179"><text>I'm not much interested in all these stalker rumors of yours. One comes in and says the army boys lost something, another comes in and says monsters crawled out of the underground, a third says the radiation, or whatever it is, got turned off... None of that matters to me. The main thing is that with those rumors, stalkers also bring good loot. If they only come in to chatter, I don't even listen.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_180"><text>They say some artifacts can drive a person mad... Only I haven't met anyone who really lost his mind because of an art.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_181"><text>I heard people sometimes find strange stones. Like there's a radio built into them. You find a stone like that and listen to it, and it tells you what's happening around the area. Someone, they say, was even shown the way to the center of the Zone. But it's a rare thing, you won't just find one.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_182"><text>Heard about cobblestones? People have recipes for transforming artifacts. So when an artifact like that passes through the final stage of transformation, it turns into a cobblestone, but not an ordinary one, a charmed one. And with that cobblestone, you can then pass wherever you want...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_183"><text>I heard the Zone was formed when a meteorite struck the ground. And on impact, the meteorite exploded. Its main mass remained there in the center, while the blast scattered fragments all over the Zone, and now people find those fragments. They aren't artifacts, of course, but you can still sell them, especially to scientists.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_184"><text>If you find an unusual stone that makes your head start humming, don't even think about keeping it on you. I heard someone picked up one like that, carried it for a while, then lost it. After that his head started humming even worse and still hums to this day. People start talking to him, and it's like he doesn't hear them, just says "huh, what?" - that's how loud the hum is in his head.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_185"><text>There's a rumor going around that some artifacts sort of talk to you. Whoever carries them starts rambling little by little... At first just a bit, then they won't shut their mouth - always saying something to someone, but when you look, there's nobody nearby. That's them talking to the artifact.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_186"><text>So many schizos have cropped up in the Zone! And the farther in, the more of them. One mumbles something about the Monolith, another says he's expected at the center of the Zone, a third starts spouting bullshit about his own uniqueness. And the most broken ones are those who start talking to themselves, then throw themselves into anomalies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_187"><text>Heard about the guy who said he was "chosen"? Someone told me recently. He was a normal man, then found either some cobblestone or just a rock, and his roof slid off. Started telling everyone he was chosen by the Zone, that he had an impossible mission and he alone could carry it out. The things the Zone does to people!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_188"><text>They say someone finds meteorite fragments. So those fragments, after lying in anomalies, take on strange properties: they affect people like some kind of hypnotic device. You don't even notice when you fall under their influence. They tell you: kill your comrade, it has to be done! And the person carrying such a fragment goes and kills.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_189"><text>Heard about the meteorite fragments? Bullshit. It wasn't a meteorite at all. I was told those are fragments of the Monolith itself! In one powerful emission the Monolith exploded, only nothing happened to it, a few fragments just flew off, and that's all. Zombies picked up those fragments and started carrying them around the Zone. And whoever now meets such a zombie with a fragment becomes a zombie himself and takes that burden from him, to carry it farther.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_190"><text>They say "Чёрная метка [TERM?]" is a cooled fragment of the Monolith itself. When it crawled up from underground, well, or from somewhere, it caught fire at first and started crackling like a heated stone. Those fragments flew off from that, and as they cooled, they lost weight. And they became, well, like dandelion seeds - the wind carried them all over the Zone. And whoever picked up such a seed of the Monolith got that same "Чёрная метка [TERM?]."</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_191"><text>Same as always. We shoot wildlife bit by bit. Enough to live on.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_192"><text>They say someone saw Burers here. If it's true, that's bad news. How did they wander here, and most importantly, from where?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_193"><text>They say there are so many dogs beyond the bridge that it's better not to poke that way alone. These dogs breed here like... cats.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_194"><text>Here, somewhere to the north, they spotted a pack of cats... or whatever cats have, a pride, devil knows, a lot of them in short. And there never used to be any. Well, fine - we'll make hats for winter.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_195"><text>A rookie showed up here recently. You could tell right away: some engineer, not a hunter. Started putting forward his efficiency proposals: let's specialize, he says, divide duties, someone hunts Tushkanos, someone hunts Boars... City smartass. If I only go after little Tushkanos, how much will I make off them? Just wasted rounds. And he, meaning, will shoot Fleshes, the most profitable beast in our parts. The men quickly explained what's what around here... Haven't seen him since. Guess he didn't like that arrangement.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_196"><text>Everything's the same here... Different people come through. Only not everyone can hunt. They think it's that simple: "bang-bang" and done. Like hell... you need skill here, need to know the beast's habits. Doesn't matter that it mutated; a beast stays a beast.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_197"><text>Recently some businesslike type showed up. Looked like one of those former chairmen, some communard. He says: "Let's live as a commune and split everything equally." This patch, he says, is Vanka's, that patch is Sanka's, that one over there is Petka's... We say: "And who the hell are you? Where's your patch?" Mine, he says, is beyond the bridge. Businesslike, right?! That's the best hunting ground there. Ignat put him in his place right away. Damn communard! We should have crushed more of them back in the day.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_198"><text>Heard about Dan? He used to be here. Then he and Ignat couldn't divide something. I don't know what happened between them, only Dan left for the Cordon somewhere. A few more guys went with him. And Ignat pretends everything is fine: he wanted to leave, so he left... A shady story.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_199"><text>Some gopniks came to Ignat recently. They talked something over between themselves, and then Ignat gathered everyone and said: we need to shoot a lot of Fleshes, big order for hides. Yeah... We had a good hunt the other day, didn't spare ammo - Ignat handed it out generously. Only the payment is unclear... He's quiet for now. Need to find out from him what's what...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_200"><text>Met some egghead here recently. He had such businesslike gear - a special suit, like a spacesuit. What are they doing here? This is practically the outskirts...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_201"><text>They say the men on the Cordon take tribute from stalkers. True, they call it contributions in favor of hunters, but whatever you call it, it's extortion. I heard Ignat gets something from it, like he has a share. Some tricky relationship they've got there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_202"><text>I heard that after an emission, wildlife starts breeding. Like some rut begins in them right after it. How else do you explain their numbers? No matter how many we kill, they never run out and never run out...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_203"><text>They say stalkers call wildlife monsters... Is that so? What's so scary about them? They told me about the Bloodsucker, and yes, that one is probably a monster... I haven't met one myself. The rest are ordinary beasts. Same pigs, just twisted a little, same Boars. Dogs are just dogs. And Tushkanos are like rats, only bigger.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_204"><text>Tried our sausage? Someone whispered to me recently that besides Flesh and Boar meat, they add dog meat too, supposedly for piquancy. It's meat too, of course, but I prefer to think it's still only pork... And we also have gourmets who smoke Tushkano legs with spices, so you can't tell them from chicken legs. Same thing, just tougher.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_205"><text>I heard Ignat ordered a whole batch of tin cans from the mainland, and some kind of device, like a mini-autoclave. Looks like we'll be making canned food ourselves now. Sidorovich will be "thrilled" about that competition.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_206"><text>I heard all kinds of people keep pestering others with stupid questions: "What have I heard?" So get lost...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_207"><text>Sidorovich has gotten completely fat and greedy! Someone says to him: "Here, take an artifact," and he turns his nose up: not the right one, he says. No, just look at this piece of work. No decency in him! Businessman...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_208"><text>Васька [TERM?] found a lighter in some house here recently. Old enough to remember Брежнев [TERM?]. And it works. Doesn't run out either, imagine that! He thought life was sweet now, savings and all. Then at the checkpoint he gave Kuznetsov a light... Handed it right into his hands! What a scatterbrain, huh? Well, at least during Kuznetsov's shift he gets through quietly, and that's something.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_209"><text>Санёк Лохматый [TERM?] bit a dog to death recently, heard that? Oh, pal, that was something. In the evening he went behind the bushes to count the stars, and then we hear someone scream! We run over and see Sanyok lying there, shit all over himself, and a blind dog on top of him. While he was counting stars, he says, he dropped his assault rifle beside him. Then he started feeling around and realized what was in his hand wasn't the rifle at all. When that something jerked toward him, he sank his teeth into it. And I don't think the dog died from fright at all. It was just old, that's what I say.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_210"><text>In the Dark Valley, some asshole sells ammo. Cheap, but those rounds are deadly if they hit you on the head from the twelfth floor... just swing harder when you throw them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_211"><text>I was at Garbage. Looks like the bandit scum got their heads beaten in hard; now it's quiet and peaceful in the hangar and at the vehicle graveyard. Duty members are good men... they can do it when they want to!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_212"><text>Sanyok told me this: he was in the Swamps. Says he is trudging along, not bothering anyone. Then he sees a fisherman sitting by a puddle. All hunched up, holding a rod, doesn't care about a thing, like he is somewhere in Подмосковье [TERM?]. Figures the man got tired of all this mess, missed fishing, and Sanyok likes that too, so he walked up to him. Says: buddy, around here you might catch a crocodile with elephant ears, but fish are a lost cause... The man turns around, and it's a dead man! Moaning, gurgling, waving some stick around. Sanyok talked and talked at him, and the thing just sat there. What kind of filth did that to a man, huh? Looks like he died, but see how it still twists him... that's how it is.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_213"><text>Why are you bothering me? What am I supposed to tell you when the only news here is another report about another stiff. Wait for the newspaper "Голос снорка [TERM?]" to come out; they'll tell you everything there, even with pictures.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_214"><text>Listen, this is impossible already. I stashed some loot recently, thought the place was perfect! Nobody would find it. But no, they got in there too! Next time I'm putting only mines in my stash. I'm sick of those rat bastards, I hate them!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_215"><text>Some scarecrow dragged in a stone here recently. The stone shone like it was greased, and this sap starts bragging: "Look how lucky I am! Unknown artifact! I'll rake in piles of cash." He sat there with that little stone in his hands, and then - bam! He got sick. Where's the exit here, he says, I can't seem to find it. Серёга Черешня [TERM?] is more experienced than most of us, so he sensed right away something was wrong, grabbed his dosimeter fast, and the scale wasn't enough! You scrawny bastard, he yells, everyone get out of here now! Turns out this clown was wandering around with no dosimeter, found that little stone everyone avoided, because it was practically glowing, fuck it! Dragged it to us, the bastard. Can't go into that house now, and my gear is still in there...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_216"><text>You know what I don't understand? Where are people's heads? They come here like it's a picnic. Guitars, songs by the fire... Last week someone ate three tourists like that. They probably didn't even have time to understand anything, let alone shoot. Fools, damn it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_217"><text>Once I was walking toward a Duty checkpoint, and I hear noise, chaos, Duty men yelling, calling everyone nearby for help because wildlife is overwhelming them! So I run, spit flying in the wind, get there, and everything is squealing, grunting, and barking. I get to work: threw every grenade I had, my rifle was practically smoking, some bastard bit through my hand, still aches... And one asshole over there, their warrant officer, says: "You're weak, no use at all"... can you imagine? I tell him: buddy, is that a joke, or are you seriously saying my help isn't worth a sniff? I say, I carry an F-1 grenade for special occasions, and for something like this I'll gift it to you right now down your collar with the pin out... Bastard. He wilted fast, the ugly mug, and now lets me into the Bar without a sound.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_218"><text>People say the army boys at Agroprom got robbed. Some slick bastard stole documents from them. It's boiling over there now, holy hell! A commission arrived, and the local captain flew to the mainland... looks like not by helicopter, but by a boot up the ass. No point sticking your nose in there now; they'll drop you at once.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_219"><text>Heard stalkers recently rescued someone at Agroprom? The army boys pinned them down. They say a fair number of people died. What a mess is going on, and why can't people live quietly? Are we at war or what? We didn't come here to fight a war... We're already walking the edge, and if we start shooting each other too, that's disaster.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_220"><text>Have you ever led tourists around these parts? No? Always an adventure with them. Someone told me: Митяй Длинный [TERM?] got mixed up with them once, because they asked very nicely. Very, very nicely... So he got the job of escorting two clowns into... in short, watching over them, yes. So there they are, walking slowly, Митяй [TERM?] tosses stones and bolts into anomalies for them, shows them a Tushkano from a distance, the standard Zone safari package, right. Then he sees one of them fidgeting, dancing in place. He says: "Why are you dancing? Need to go?" The man flashes his little glasses, like yes, that's the issue. Митяй [TERM?] crawled through the bushes first, checked it was all clear. Go fertilize the Zone, he says...\n
They stand and wait. He tells the other one: "Keep the rifle ready, friend, and stand with your back to me, or you'll fire from fright, empty head with ears." Then they hear a voice - the shitter is mumbling something: hello, he says, allow me to introduce myself, I am so-and-so, associate professor of the department... They go to him. And they see this egghead has already pulled up his pants and is standing there talking to a Snork! The thing must have fallen asleep or something... unclear. Митяй [TERM?] puts one into its skull right away before it wakes up - bang! And that little shitter screams: "Murderer, criminal, madman!" Then the second one catches up: "What have you done, this is a crime, you can't kill the mentally ill, this is some kind of fascism"... Митяй [TERM?] didn't get it at first, then figured it out: they mistook the Snork for a psycho in a gas mask. He led them closer: look, he says, see what kind of little animal this is. They started puking right away!.. But after that, he says, they walked quiet as mice, step after step. Eggheads...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_221"><text>Heard a mutant has appeared in the Zone? Looks completely human from the outside. But appearances deceive, right? So this scarecrow walks up to everyone he meets and asks: "What new can you tell me?" You'll give him the news, remember every last piece of gossip, even make new ones up just to appease that ghoul, and he still keeps hammering: "What new can you tell me?.." You haven't run into that mutant by chance, have you?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_222"><text>They say there's a lake called Yantar here. Nothing but zombies wandering around there, in crowds... Walking and moaning. They said those zombies gather in hangars, walk through factory workshops, sit in broken sheds. And they also said that by that lake there's a mobile bunker, and it's been standing there since the first time everything blew. And zombies sit there in white coats, from back then, can you imagine? Everything proper: guards walk around, those little lab coats run out to take samples, worms have eaten everything out of them, but they still twitch there and wander around... Horror!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_223"><text>Everything's rotten... On the Cordon they caught one little creep - a quick type, here one moment, there the next... Filled our ears with lies, the little nightingale. If you see him, send greetings from the crew. We remember him...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_224"><text>What can I say, we're dying out... Zone here, Zone there. The cops in choppers are killing our crew, and beasts roam in herds. Everyone's so sharp, so lively...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_225"><text>Been to Garbage? In short, some shady outsiders rolled up on the drifters there, and their boss is a devil... or what's his name - Bes, you know him? He made a claim, like: you clueless riffraff, clear out while it's quiet, we'll hold the line here and manage without you. The boys didn't understand: there was no agreement, and they weren't talking by the code... Then those brutes pulled out guns and put almost everyone down. Scumbags... We'll straighten that devil's horns for him...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_226"><text>Once the boys and I were standing around, and some creep comes striding toward us from the forest edge, a brazen moose of a man, antlers to the sky, not a care in the world. And Knysh [TERM?] is a serious man, so he shouts to him: "Wait up, buddy. You're walking down this road, but you don't know that the boys guarding this path have a hard time sometimes."\n
That moose puffed up at first, stood there glaring, then opened his mouth and shouted at us, like, boys, I have no cash, no food, I'm not local, and please let me go, sirs. Knysh [TERM?] tells him: "Nobody is holding you. Why did you panic? Go on your way... Only the crew asks you to share what you can, out of the kindness of your heart. We're not robbing you like snot-nosed street punks, you're hurting our feelings." So he takes the sack off his back and drags out a little wheel of sausage. Knysh [TERM?] takes it and says: "Thanks, man, only here's the trouble: there are this many of us here, and this isn't enough... Look, Kolyan's [TERM?] boots are completely shot, and you've got real good combat boots, and that cloak is decent too, so share a little. You'll find yourself more gear, you're a lucky man, anyone can see that"...\n
And that moose forces out a grin and shouts: "Now you've got luck too - yours, forever." Knysh [TERM?] swelled up a bit, and we look at his hands, and it's not sausage there, but some black piece of shit, like a drop! Knysh [TERM?] starts squealing something about a mark, we aim to drop that creep, but he's gone already, imagine that! Vanished like the earth swallowed him. Only Knysh [TERM?] started rushing around like a cockroach, then flew straight into an anomaly, even though we'd walked that spot a hundred times... That's the kind of mess it was, buddy.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_227"><text>Found yourself a storyteller, have you? Want me to sing too, and dance? Sure, I can, just whistle...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_228"><text>Leave me alone... Some filth cut up a friend of mine recently. He had a decent rifle. Some creature stabbed him at night. Ah...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_229"><text>There is such a phenomenon as mutant psi-influence on humans. Have you ever experienced anything like it? Yes? Most unpleasant sensations, wouldn't you agree?</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_230"><text>Last week I was taking measurements... And imagine, something came over me that cannot be explained from a scientific point of view. My vision suddenly went dark and... I saw a pack of rats. A huge pack. Everything was swarming with them. Then it let me go, I looked, and there were no rats, never had been. What it means, I do not understand.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_231"><text>Ever run into Burers? They say they're like hamsters: they drag anything they find into their burrow. And whatever doesn't fit, they carry around with them. The men here said they gutted one of those Burer storehouses. What a fight that was - there was all kinds of stuff in there! Canned food, boots, ammo, not counting empty junk. Where they gathered it all, who knows... Only who the hell needs that around here. Well, the smarter men waited until all kinds of fools smashed each other's noses over the junk, then went for the real loot... They grabbed a decent haul, they say. Lied about half of it, of course, maybe more, but some of it must be true...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_232"><text>Heard they saw a woman somewhere? Around the Swamps, supposedly... I feel like taking a walk. It's not like I really need it, but sometimes you want to squeeze something warm and springy a little...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_233"><text>You didn't see what happened here... Some kid came running. Still far off, he yells: "Bloodsucker! Watch out, crew!" So we scattered wherever we could, hid and watched... And this transparent mug runs up to Диман копчёный [TERM?]. He'd dozed off a little after yesterday and sat down by the gate. And chomp! Bit Диман [TERM?]'s head off. We stood there with our mouths open, and it tucked what was left under its arm and ran from us. We still didn't really figure out what it was... a Bloodsucker, or some other crap that appeared.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_234"><text>On the hill a fellow stands, and he cannot pass the land: over him a "Whirligig," all around the "Jelly" big, then a Chimera came to play, start the fairy tale again...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_235"><text>We had one junkie, a terrible murky type, always walking around wasted. He preyed on stalkers who were crawling half-dead, barely alive. Watched for them on the paths, saw someone and right away: "Buddy, let me help. Ah, look how badly you're twisted up," while he gave him a little kiss with a knife and stole his things. Pure butcher, dark soul. Nobody went on jobs with him, too nasty, and anyway...\n
So he would have kept rustling around by himself. Then one day he came back covered in blood. Shaking, moaning. He had his own corner where he cooked his junk and food, always hid there. And then you could hear him mumbling there. A junkie is a junkie, people like that always grumble something, but this one sounded like he was talking to someone, like he was making excuses. Then he screamed: "Go away! Go away, I killed you already." Enough! The boys and I kicked him outside, he yelled out there and went quiet... In the morning the crew shouts: that junkie hanged himself on a poplar, and so neatly he was right at the top. How he climbed up there, hell knows. That's the kind of crap it was...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_236"><text>Listen, who are you anyway? Walking around here, asking questions... Whose are you, mister? You should leave while you can...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_237"><text>Listen here: life for us is hard and sad. We all walk under God, and we also walk under our boss. So, buddy, imagine how hard a crust of bread comes to us. Stalkers are all cocky. You come to one with your whole soul, and he tries to put a bullet in your forehead, bullish ugly bastard. They walk around, throwing their weight around, but they can't keep order. They don't want to help the boys and they get greedy. So we keep spinning...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_238"><text>Heard about the underground? The boys poked in there, and there was this huge door. We thought: nice, maybe we can dig up something there. But no way in... Tough luck.</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_239"><text>Every day brings news from every district. Just keep your ears spread wide and hang more noodles on them...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_240"><text>What's new here? Same old. We get chewed out every other day: you get the loot, we get the duty roster. They chase us like Sidor's goats...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_241"><text>My combat boots are shot. And the quartermaster won't issue new ones. Probably drank them away... sick of all this shit!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_242"><text>I'm sick of it all! An anomaly here, a stalker charging in there with a sawed-off! What is it for you out there, smeared with honey or something? The colonel came by, spitting all over: "Why aren't you securing it, why are you violating orders, why, why ...?" Let him stand here himself! Demob can't come soon enough!</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_243"><text>Not much new with us... The boys here are untested, and they send them here right away. I feel sorry for them...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_244"><text>You know, in our unit there's a stone. Not here... back there, beyond the perimeter. It's called Fallen at a Combat Post... But where are the battles? Who is fighting whom here? Damn Zone, curse it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_cool_info_245"><text>Heard a Burer was here - insane! Three meters tall! And someone put it down, imagine that! Lucky bastards. A hulk like that must have had a pile of artifacts...</text></string>

<string id="dm_help_thanks_1"><text>Thank you very much.</text></string>

<string id="dm_intro_0"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_1"><text>Well, hello.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_10"><text>Hello! Duty runs everything here. Keep that in mind if you don't want trouble.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_100"><text>Well, hello.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_101"><text>Good day.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_102"><text>At your service.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_103"><text>Hello, man!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_104"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_105"><text>Oh, hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_106"><text>Hello.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_107"><text>Greetings.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_108"><text>Hello, stalker!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_109"><text>Greetings, stalker!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_11"><text>Hello! You're on Duty territory. Rules are simple here: treat everyone like a human being, and everything will be fine.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_110"><text>Hello, stalker!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_111"><text>Hello there!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_112"><text>Hi, man!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_113"><text>Aloha!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_114"><text>Hello, man!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_115"><text>Hey, you, why are you here? Keep moving.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_116"><text>What do you need?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_117"><text>Well? Keep walking.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_118"><text>Move along. Nothing to stare at.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_119"><text>Well, what do you want?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_12"><text>Good health to you!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_13"><text>I don't have time for chatter. Go on, head to the Bar.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_14"><text>Oh, hello! Better not get close to the factory. It's a dead place.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_15"><text>Hello, stalker! Be careful here: dead men keep pouring out of the complex.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_16"><text>Hello. Are you here on business?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_17"><text>Salute!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_18"><text>Hello! Want some advice? Don't even think about going past Барьер [TERM?] - some kind of radiation there will fry your brains in no time!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_19"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_2"><text>Hey there!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_20"><text>Hey! Heard about the Scorcher? From here it's already within arm's reach, so I don't advise pushing farther north.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_21"><text>Well, hello! I see you're a risk-taker too, since you weren't afraid to poke your nose into Radar. Keep your eyes open, it's very dangerous here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_22"><text>Greetings! Terrible place, isn't it?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_23"><text>Oh, a living soul! Uh... you are alive, aren't you?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_24"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_25"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_26"><text>Hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_27"><text>Well, what are you shaking here for? Got something to say, say it!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_28"><text>What are you staring at? Who the hell are you?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_29"><text>What do you want, little punk?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_30"><text>Come on then, start rattling about that... what is it... the Bolshoi Theater.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_31"><text>And what kind of bird is this? Got some business, or what?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_3"><text>Hello, man! You don't happen to have vodka on you, do you? Don't think it's for me, I need to grease the soldiers for passage under the bridge. I'd pay you back later... somehow.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_4"><text>Oh, hello! How are you holding up?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_5"><text>Hello, hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_6"><text>Well, hello!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_7"><text>Hello! Any idea why the army boys got so fired up around here the other day?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_8"><text>How are things, fellow stalker? My advice to you: don't deal with the local gopniks.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_9"><text>Hey, stalker! You shouldn't hang around here too much. The thieves have a den nearby, so running into trouble is easy as breathing.</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_1"><text>Buddy, help!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_10"><text>Somebody help!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_11"><text>Guard, I'm wounded! To me!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_12"><text>Help! I'm dying!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_13"><text>Buddy... Medkit... I'm dying... Help!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_19"><text>Hey! Help me out....</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_20"><text>Don't leave me! Medkit... </text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_14"><text>Stalker... give me a medkit... I'm dying... Help me, and I'll help you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_15"><text>Stalker... give me a medkit... I'm dying... Help me, and I'll help you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_16"><text>Stalker... give me a medkit... I'm dying... Help me, and I'll help you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_17"><text>Stalker... give me a medkit... I'm dying... Help me, and I'll help you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_18"><text>Stalker... give me a medkit... I'm dying... Help me, and I'll help you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_2"><text>Boys, medkit!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_3"><text>Medkit over here!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_4"><text>Anti-shock, boys! Hurry!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_5"><text>Medkit, men!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_6"><text>Somebody!.. Give me a medkit!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_7"><text>Friend, medkit... medkit!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_8"><text>Help me, man!</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_9"><text>Share a medkit, friend, huh?</text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_21"><text>Buddy! Medkit... </text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_22"><text>Stalker, friend... Help... </text></string>
<string id="dm_intro_help_23"><text>Hey, help me, man... Medkit... </text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_101"><text>I'd love to put every last Monolith member down, damn them! Those Monolith members, motherfuckers... Their roofs have completely slid off. There was a time when they were still peaceful... I remember meeting one in the Zone once, and of course he started up his Monolith drivel again, like: "Brothers, the Monolith called to me in the night. I spoke with it. It was beautiful in its majesty. I nearly went blind, but its light filled me with great power! I know, I feel that its power abides with us all! It told me that only firm faith can defeat evil. It told me its power will fill only the faithful. It also revealed to me that our victory is near," and I told him: "Go to hell with your Monolith!" He boiled over and yelled: "The time will come, and we will cleanse the Zone of unbelievers!" and all that. Looks like the bastard wasn't lying: now they've gone completely feral, pouring out of the CNPP in crowds, shooting everyone without distinction, totally out of their minds!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_102"><text>I feel like smoking... Got matches? You don't smoke? Ah, no luck for me today...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_103"><text>I'll go talk with the men... You, young stalker, if you see a PDA message about Семецкий [TERM?]'s death, don't get distracted. It's one of the Zone's legends. That message will come to you more than once. They say Семецкий [TERM?] is one of those who managed to reach the Monolith. What did he ask for? Right, immortality. So now he crawls around the Zone, dying over and over. Some people have even seen him, though they might be lying. Ah, Zone, you are full of secrets and riddles... Have I bothered you too much with my legends? Fine then, go in peace. Good hunting.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_104"><text>Want me to tell you a joke? Three stalkers argued over which of them was tougher, and decided this: whoever drives more people out of the stalker bar is the toughest. The first grabs a heavy machine gun, bursts into the bar: \n- Everyone out, now! - half the crowd clears out, but ten stalkers stay behind and give him such a beating he barely gets out.\nThe next day, the second one does some trick, pretends to be a mutant, and slips into the bar. The crowd scatters, some through the window, some through the door, but a Duty squad stays behind and beats him half to death. A couple days later, the third one just walks into the bar and starts coughing from the doorway: \n- Kha-kkha-ghuhu-ghuhu-kha, hrrrk-ptooey! Damn syphilis!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_105"><text>I'll go to the men and hear some new stories... Want me to tell you one? There is this story, supposedly true, happened long ago, long before I got here myself. So, here it is... Some foreigner decided to become a stalker, to make money, supposedly; he was some kind of scientist, I think... Hell knows what he wanted here, but he barely understood a damn word of Russian... And really, nobody knows how he even reached the Zone and Barkeep. Someone outside the Zone recommended Barkeep to him. So he didn't understand Russian worth a damn, though he thought otherwise... Started pestering Barkeep in broken language... Barkeep fought with him for a couple hours. The man either needed to get somewhere or wanted to find someone... In short, Barkeep didn't understand anything clearly and decided to send that weirdo to Freedom territory. He tells him: go here and there, that territory is controlled by Freedom fighters, they'll explain everything to you. Back then, for some reason, people still thought Freedomers were on good terms with English. So from everything Barkeep said, that foreign miracle somehow liked the word "control," since it's the same for them in English, and when he came to Freedom he started questioning everyone: "Control, Controller, Controller," waving his hand toward Duty and repeating his line. They say Freedom got scared badly, raised the whole camp, and it was night too; they stood watch on the towers until morning. That guy was later kicked out of Freedom, and Duty never saw him after that either. I doubt he found what he was looking for in the Zone...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_106"><text>Lots of people have turned into "trash pickers" now. Before, nobody even looked in the heaps: so much radiation it would hard-boil your balls in half an hour. But now that loot has gotten scarce, they wrap themselves in protection, take some chems, and off they go digging. You can find all kinds of things there, though mostly small stuff.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_107"><text>I need to rest... Rookies have gotten completely brazen lately. They climb into anomalies and die, die, die... In the last two days, imagine it, five young stalkers vanished. And do they get even a little more careful? Not a damn bit. Муха [TERM?] recently took three blockheads into his squad. Where are they now? And he came back with loot, made a nice haul too. Maybe he killed them himself? No, probably not... he's honest... relatively. Anyway, from what I can see you're a rookie too, so keep your eyes open. Good luck.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_108"><text>I'm sitting here thinking... Do you know about the classified laboratories deep in the Zone?.. Supposedly they're still operating... Yeah, yeah... Hard to understand how anyone could have survived there at all, with no supplies, no power... So the question is: maybe it isn't people working there? I talked to one type here... He didn't see the laboratories himself. No, not himself, but on a scanner at Yantar he picked up some strange transmissions. They talked about some laboratory. And another man swore to that first one that he once ran into a figure in a suit like a stalker's, but more advanced. And supposedly that half-transparent figure told him to get the hell out of there. "Don't interfere, leave, we're working here." Well, the guy shit himself... naturally! Which of us had ever seen anything like that before?.. On the other hand, it supposedly happened near Radar... Yeah. So it's probably not true... But then again... mutations can be different, probably. Maybe they aren't people anymore, but some kind of energy entities? Huh?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_109"><text>What business is it of yours where I'm going? I roam the Zone with my own buddies, and we don't need freeloaders.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_110"><text>Nothing yet... Want a joke? A pack of rats is running along. A stalker steps out in front of them: "Any tough guys here?" he asks. "No." "Then one artifact from every rat, and keep running." Next day, same thing! The rats decide to call in a Blind Dog. They run. The stalker steps out and stops the pack: "Any tough guys here?" The rats part, and the Blind Dog steps out: "Well, I guess I'm tough." The stalker steps aside, and a Controller comes out: "All right, ten artifacts from the tough ones, one from everyone else! And keep running!"</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_111"><text>I'm thinking of learning more about the factions... Listen, man, do you know anything solid about "Перехват [TERM?]"? They say they're specialists, career military! But the way they work, huh?! The way they work! These aren't the assholes at the checkpoints! Not only do they crawl into the deepest shit, they sit in the Zone for months! I'm not making it up! They have bases, several at once, tons of caches, and helicopters keep dropping supplies near the perimeter for them. Their commander is some Громов [TERM?]... I think the surname is fake, not real; they call him either "Major" or "Гром [TERM?]." Don't believe me?! Пахомыч [TERM?] once caught a Перехват [TERM?] transmission! Caught it and ran like hell, or they would have killed him for nothing... Secrecy, damn it! Everyone knows Пахомыч [TERM?], right? There you go! It's not bullshit, it's a serious outfit. Hell knows what they found so interesting here, but they work like you wouldn't believe! If I worked even a third that well - no, ten percent that well! - I'd already have built myself a ten-story house in Сочах [TERM?]... They say they have a gadget that spots monsters from two hundred meters away. Any creature! Clear as day, then you can stroll through the Zone and spit as you go... And then, they say, there are some other operators too. Not military, more like our kind... In short, some of them made it to the center of the Zone. Not only made it, they say they can tame creatures too! They don't go outside the perimeter to the mainland at all, and nobody goes to them either... well, except maybe those who were born with a path to the Саркофаг [TERM?] written in their fate. They have so many artifacts they could wipe their asses with them! Duty members know about them well... they know, the bastards, they fight them, and keep quiet! Ask any of those cops and he says: "Fairy tales." Well, aren't they fuckers, huh?!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_112"><text>What are you even talking about... Something happened here... I had a disaster, fucked away my backpack full of loot. Just like that! I thought I'd come back with a big payday, but then disaster: at night a blind dog popped out from under the bushes and growled at me. I nearly shit my pants from fear, even mistook it for a Pseudodog at first, because you can hear blind dogs coming, but those things are silent. So I threw my backpack and ran! At first I thought that bastard would chase me, but it grabbed the backpack and vanished in some unknown direction. I'll go on a new run. By the way, don't want to come with me? No? Fine then, see you.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_113"><text>I'm thinking of going out for loot, but they say there's a Controller there... Though I heard that during emissions, Controllers glitch out hard and can't do anything, basically, so you can take them barehanded...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_114"><text>Relax, stop fussing... Here's a joke, a little dumb but funny. \nIn the evening, stalkers are sitting in a tavern, drinking beer, telling stalker tales... \nOne says: \n- The other day in the Zone I met a monster this bi-i-ig, emptied all my ammo into it, barely put it down with a grenade launcher. \nEveryone: \n- Who-o-oa! \nThe second says: \n- And yesterday in the Zone I saw a monster this bi-i-i-ig, emptied all my ammo into it, grenades didn't touch it, only dropped it with a flamethrower. \nEveryone: \n- Who-o-o-oa! \nThe third says: \n- And today in the Zone a monster THIS BI-I-I-I-IG spotted me... \nEveryone at once: \n- Wha-a-at? \nThe stalker says calmly: \n- What do you mean, what? I barely washed my pants clean back at base!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_115"><text>I want to learn more about different stalkers... Have you heard of Проводник [TERM?]? The very first stalker. The first to start going into the Zone, and still alive. They say he'll guide you anywhere. The problem is finding him: he doesn't put up posters with his address... And he doesn't agree to guide just anyone either. Supposedly he takes plenty of cash, but if you found him and made a deal, be sure he'll get you where you need to go, solid as iron. That's who I'd like to talk with. He must have seen what lies beyond Radar...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_116"><text>I should get some sleeping pills, maybe... You know what I'll tell you? In this part of the Zone, you can barely sleep... I'm lucky, I can't fall asleep anyway, but people get such nightmares that sometimes they don't wake up in the morning... heart rupture, for example. Some die, others have their roofs torn clean off... Recently a rumor went around that there is a remedy. If you absolutely have to sleep, you should find an old bucket... or at least a big pot... a wash boiler, maybe... Main thing is that it's whole. Stick your head in it and sleep safe as a baby. Laugh, go on. I'll look at you in a couple days when you start falling over from exhaustion. Smartass... But tell me yourself, why the hell have the army boys started wandering around here in fancy helmets lately? Exactly! For two years or so, not a word, not a sign, and lately they keep showing up! Their helmets are some new kind; the boys found one body and told me. There was a mesh inside, made of thin copper wire, fastened to the liner. So think about it: what kind of harness is that, and what the hell is it for? And in general, that "bzz-bzz-bzz" is not for nothing, I'm telling you. There's not much to pick from anomalies here - wrong grounds, other sectors are safer and have fatter pieces too... My thinking is, they're marking approaches. Preparing a bridgehead. They want to break through to the Саркофаг [TERM?], mark my words. Soon it's going to blow so hard nobody will think it is little. Mark my words... Main thing is to be far away from here when it happens.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_117"><text>I'm getting my weapon ready just in case... Heard the news, huh? Yesterday there was a brutal massacre in the neighboring camp. Mercenaries did it, their style: cut everyone up. Looks like the sentry fell asleep at his post, and those monsters took a blade to his throat, and that was that, remember him as he was. Then they did the same to his sleeping buddies. None of our people even heard shots, that's how it was...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_118"><text>I want to learn more about the Zone... Did I tell you about Чёрный Сталкер [TERM?]? There's a legend, you see. They say some strange stalker appeared in the Zone; who he is, where he's from, and what he does, nobody knows. He wears a black cloak with the hood pulled up so you can't see his face, and carries no weapon. Only a few people have seen him at all, and from a distance at that, and they say unimaginable terror came over everyone who looked at him. They say even monsters shy away from him. Who is he, huh? Some say he's a new mutant, others say a ghost, and others say it's all tales from drunk stalkers and he doesn't exist at all. Hell knows... until I see him with my own eyes, I won't believe it.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_119"><text>I don't know yet, I only got here recently. For now I'm sitting here, getting my bearings.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_120"><text>I sat here and listened to all kinds of stories... What devil pulled me into coming to the Zone! I'm thinking of getting out of here while it's not too late.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_121"><text>I want to go see the army boys. They say you can buy some rounds from them. The local trader only gives ammo for artifacts, and where am I supposed to find him an artifact...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_122"><text>Nothing... A hair of the dog would be nice, that's all my plans for now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_123"><text>The trader here offers jobs to choose from. There are a couple simple ones nearby, just run out and back. I'm thinking, should I take one? Only I need to scrounge up ammo somewhere first. It's nearby, sure, but who knows...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_124"><text>Heard shooting at the ATP? You don't know who's there now, whether there are bandits? I need to head that way, but I'm thinking I'll wait for now. They say bandits were seen recently, and I don't feel like meeting them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_125"><text>Someone told me you can find artifacts a little farther out. They even say there's some way around the post. I should try it. What am I sitting here for?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_126"><text>Where am I going now with this leg... A couple days ago I flew into an anomaly. Good thing I only caught it with the very edge and got thrown aside. Twisted my leg, still hurts, maybe even a crack in the bone, it aches that badly.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_127"><text>The other day someone whispered to me about a stash, so I decided to crawl out and look. Then Boars charged me... I sat on some rocks for two hours. At first I thought about shooting them, then figured I had too little buckshot, to hell with that, I'd only make them angry and they'd never leave. Today I want to try getting through again, only around that place.</text></string>


<!-- Сталкеры -->
<string id="dm_action_info_128"><text>My partner and I are getting ready to take a walk. We're preparing for a run, so don't get in the way...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_129"><text>I'm not going anywhere. I'll sit here for a while. I'm tired of roaming the Zone already, should rest a bit. I've got money, food, and vodka for now, so I can relax.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_130"><text>I'll think of something. Maybe wander farther out somewhere people don't even go... Haven't decided yet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_131"><text>Why are you interested? You think an experienced stalker will just tell you where he's going and why? Only rookies flap their tongues. So come on, keep walking...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_132"><text>I'm sick of roaming the Zone. I'm thinking maybe I should join Duty. What do you think? Seems they have decent supplies there. I don't care much about their idea; the main thing is I'll have everything I need... And if needed, I can probably earn something too... Need to think it over.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_133"><text>Heard about anomalous fields? Artifacts form around those fields, and if you hurry and rush there right after an emission, you can make good money. I'll wait for an emission, sit it out, then go. I know one place.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_134"><text>I'm thinking of doing a little repair work. See how my suit got shredded? Dogs attacked, I had just shot them down, and then Tushkanos piled on. Barely fought them off, but I did get some loot. Though all that loot might go into repairs, but fine, we'll see...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_135"><text>I left supplies in one noticeable place, but I can't remember where... I was a little drunk then, treating radiation. I remember a dry tree lying there and a big rock nearby, but where exactly, I can't remember. I want to take a walk, maybe I'll orient myself by the terrain.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_136"><text>Do you think scientists accept different monster limbs? I was told they need them. I should go to their bunker and haggle. I put down a Bloodsucker the other day, still have tails from dogs, and I chased Boars too, so I've got something from them as well...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_137"><text>Last week I put down a Chimera. Ran from it a long time, dodged, but beat it. While I was running, I had to drop my backpack, and I didn't notice exactly where. Good thing I had a cache. An experienced stalker always has a couple stashes with supplies. Now I'm thinking maybe I should go look for it, maybe my little backpack is still lying there... If it were empty, I wouldn't think twice; no loss. But there was something in it. I'll probably go.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_138"><text>I'm going to see a buddy, he's nearby. I'll check my stash while I'm at it, because you know how it goes: you barely put something down before some bastard is already sniffing around. My advice to you is, if you hide something, hide it so it doesn't get searched, or later you'll be biting your own elbows. Free advice from an experienced stalker. You'll remember me yet.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_139"><text>I want to find one bastard. That ugly mug screwed me over badly and ran off. Fine, the Zone puts bastards like that on their knees first. We'll see.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_140"><text>Fuck, another curious one... Get lost, it's none of your business where I'm going.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_141"><text>What-what... Nothing. People do things, and that's fine, so what do you care?...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_142"><text>We're drinking today. Took some nice loot... heh-heh, and those idiots didn't even understand a thing, the suckers.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_143"><text>Found a spot by the road. You can calmly load up on loot there, and nobody sees you. The work is nothing, loot comes right into your hands, you only need time to search...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_144"><text>I want to get away somewhere farther. The army boys ran a raid here recently. There was serious shooting. I sat it out in the basement, but one guy got shot. I barely even knew him, he'd only just come to us, and there you go, a bullet right away. Why play the hero? Should have sat quietly in the basement and kept his head down, but no, everyone wants to be Rambo...</text></string>
<!-- Долг -->
<string id="dm_action_info_145"><text>Bandits have lost all fear, they're killing our people. They've got some kind of base in the Dark Valley, and soon we're going to destroy their snake pit.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_146"><text>I should run to base for ammo, I'm running out. Our command has started saving supplies for some reason, must be preparing for something.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_147"><text>One of our fighters vanished. He went to the Dark Valley, and for more than two days now, not a word. There's a bandit nest there, so the men and I are thinking of scouting it for now, figuring how to pin them all to the wall later.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_148"><text>I need to work on my weapon while there's time. It's shooting badly now for some reason. Because who knows - today it's quiet, tomorrow a raid by some filth, or a march somewhere.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_149"><text>I don't know, I just got back from a raid. I want to rest and sleep it off...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_150"><text>You know we've got friction with Freedom? Command told us to get all gear in order and be ready, not waste rounds. Looks like there'll be a scrap soon, so we need to prepare.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_151"><text>I'm not planning anything... Well, maybe I'll go to the Bar.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_152"><text>Nothing special... Same as always: booze, snacks, a joint... girls - virtual ones, true... ha-ha.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_153"><text>Tomorrow we're going after Bloodsuckers, that's what the boss said. True, he's been saying that for a week now. In the evening he plans to clear the village the next day, and by morning all he can think about is a hair of the dog. We'll see how it goes this time.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_154"><text>I lost my gun the other day. It was a good gun, not like this one. It's not that I was that drunk, I just leaned it somewhere because it was getting in the way of raising my glass... Need to look for where I left it. Or maybe the men are joking around, hid it somewhere themselves and think I'll buy it back... sure, keep dreaming.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_155"><text>Everyone was told not to scatter their junk around, keep it ready. And check your weapons too, touch them up if needed... Are we going after Boars or something? Or maybe we're expecting Duty to visit... </text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_156"><text>There's a rumor we'll be marching soon. I really don't feel like it... We've already settled into this place, quiet, calm, nobody bothers us... What got into their heads, going somewhere?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_157"><text>We were sitting with the men, smoking some weed... Well, puffed a little and fine, but then one fool got going and ate all the food, barely dragged him away. Now we need to look for provisions, because they say we're going somewhere soon, so we should have supplies.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_158"><text>I'm not doing anything. I'm sick of it all. This vodka has worn me down. I used to be normal, and now I've become a drunk here. Time to quit. Today I'll just fix myself up and quit, definitely... No, not today. Better on Monday.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_159"><text>I want to get a proper gun, something like a Beretta. For real men, a Beretta is just right.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_action_info_160"><text>We're going on a job soon, so we should at least prepare - drink a little while there's time, because later there won't be any...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_action_info_161"><text>I'm sick of slaving for the Boss. Why is that bastard always unhappy - this isn't enough, that isn't enough, where, and where from... He keeps thinking people want to cheat him. Sure, he's the authority, but you still have to trust your own people, seriously.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_action_info_162"><text>Fuck off! Who are you to ask questions here? Just a little runt, so go stand closer to the shitter.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_163"><text>Some sucker told us where stalkers pass through. Perfect, now we'll take them while they're warm.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_164"><text>None of your business.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_165"><text>I'm planning to shoot you... Relax, that's humor.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_166"><text>I'd like to take a nap while there's time. And you keep walking, don't hang around here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_167"><text>Do you have a business proposal? No? Then why the hell are you bothering me...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_168"><text>Offer something for good pay, maybe we'll discuss it. Then I'll decide what to do.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_169"><text>I'm not planning to do anything. And if I were, I sure wouldn't discuss it with you.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_170"><text>Don't stick your nose where it doesn't belong, you'll stay in one piece.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_171"><text>Ask fewer questions. We don't like that here.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_172"><text>What, where, when?.. Maybe you want my plans in writing?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_173"><text>I should run out for a piece of hardware, check something.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_174"><text>I was about to leave here for somewhere farther away, but I spent almost all my rounds on dogs and ruined my gun. And where am I going now without ammo and a decent weapon... I'll have to wait a bit.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_175"><text>I want to rest. I'm dead tired. Didn't go that far, but I had to run from those little rats - they're called Tushkanos.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_176"><text>I played with a guard here. Won nicely, but what can you take from him? He only offers vodka. I want to try my luck in the Bar. They say you can win artifacts there. That's a more solid prize than this bootleg.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_177"><text>That's it, I've sat here long enough, I'm sick of it! "Artifacts, artifacts..." and there's nothing decent here, just Jellyfish. I'm going deeper into the Zone. There, yes, those aren't artifacts, those are Artifacts with a capital A!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_178"><text>They say my buddy was seen somewhere at Garbage. I want to take a walk there, just need to gather my things and go.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_179"><text>My head has been splitting lately. Especially after the emission. Never had that before. They supposedly sell some kind of headache medicine in the Bar, that's what I was told. I should go there, because my head is about to crack... Or maybe I'm already turning into a zombie? Someone told a story like that. God forbid... No, I need to get to the Bar urgently. At least I'll drink there and my head will pass.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_180"><text>I'll go to the Bar soon. Do you know where to get a decent gun for money? Here it's only for arts, and even then just Kalashes. I want something more solid. The men say go to the Bar, maybe someone there will offer something.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_181"><text>I'll sit here for now. I don't want to go anywhere. I should look around and get used to this area, then I'll decide what to do.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_182"><text>They say a stalker died somewhere nearby. Very recently. I'll go rummage around, maybe there's still something I can pull off him. And don't look at me like that... everyone does it. He doesn't care anymore, and we still have to live somehow.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_183"><text>I heard you can find different recipes to cook a bad artifact into a good one, or a good one into a super-good one. Only everyone keeps quiet like fish, nobody wants to talk. Everyone thinks only he should have that super-duper little recipe. But if it's such valuable information, there has to be someone who sells it. Need to find that trader.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_184"><text>Damn it! I recently made a deal with Sidorovich for dog tails, ran around all day, burned through so many rounds. Well, I brought them, and he had disappeared somewhere. What do I need those tails for? I sold them. Then Sidorovich shows up: "Where are my tails?" Where was he wandering?! Now I have to chase dogs again. That's exactly what I'm getting ready to do.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_185"><text>I'm going to the Swamps. Someone just whispered to me about a path... only I won't tell you. Find your own path.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_186"><text>We dug up a lot in a week. Now we need to sell it. I'll make the rounds of my stashes and go to the traders.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_187"><text>Bandit scum has worn us down. They keep coming and coming... like cockroaches - squash one, and another is already peeking from behind the baseboard. We want to crush them all.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_188"><text>I have only one plan: gather as much as I can and sell it for as much as I can. What else do you need?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_189"><text>I should patch up my armor somewhere. There was supposedly some craftsman sitting on the Cordon, and one in the Bar too. Maybe I should stop by... one or the other.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_190"><text>Turns out you can get to Санаторий [TERM?]. I don't know the road, but our people are getting ready to go, so I'll go with them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_191"><text>They said Agroprom is swimming in artifacts. Probably lying, but it wouldn't hurt to check.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_192"><text>You know, there are some laboratories... The men said it's better not to poke your nose in there. But I'd be interested to see what's inside.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_193"><text>I'll go somewhere to Garbage. There's a bandit snake pit not far from here, and I'm sick of them already. You walk carefully. They can be worse than monsters.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_194"><text>Why go anywhere when it's good here? We've got everything for now - food, drink. It's quiet here, calm. Live and let live.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_195"><text>I don't like those Duty grunts. I don't like being ordered around. Freedom, now that's what I need. There you're your own master. I should get closer to them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_196"><text>Our plans are simple: crush every bastard who carries filth out of the Zone. First we'll smash Freedom, then the bandits, and then we'll deal with stalkers too, if they don't settle down by then. They keep finding all kinds of filth and dragging it to traders. That's how this infection spreads.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_197"><text>Whatever we plan to do, our cause was, is, and always will be righteous.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_198"><text>We've been killing those Freedom deadbeats, and we'll keep killing them. That is our goal and task right now.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_199"><text>Looks like you've got nothing to do? Then run to the Bar and sign up, then into formation! Meaning, into our orderly ranks.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_200"><text>What is there to do now? We'll rest, relax... and tomorrow back to the post.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_201"><text>No matter how you look at it, I have to go on duty again. They say: "Show some civic spirit, we're short on men..." What civic spirit, damn it, when for a month now I've been strapping on the duty belt every other day? I don't remember even the army being like this. Idlers like you wear out your pants at the Bar, and I, apparently, have to show civic spirit for all of you...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_202"><text>I misplaced my PDA somewhere. Need to look for it. Or maybe someone's stealing them from our boys, since this isn't the first case... If I find out, I'll kill him on the spot!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_203"><text>Why did I ever join Duty? I used to do stalker work too. Maybe I should drop all this and go back... if they let me, which they probably won't. Yeah... I'm in deep.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_204"><text>As always, we'll establish order... a new order! Everyone as one, orderly ranks! And all sorts of unbelievers, like the junkies from Freedom, we'll root them out. No funny business! We'll get what we want! Everyone will march as one!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_205"><text>Our task is simple - rid the Earth of this plague. That's what we do every day, and what we'll keep doing. And it's time for you to understand it, meaning let our idea sink in. You look like a decent man - not spoiled by the Zone yet. So there's only one road for you - to us, to Duty.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_206"><text>What? You give a damn about my plans and what I'm going to do? Get lost!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_207"><text>We're going on a job soon. Going to collect some "debts" from the Duty grunts. How long can we put up with their shakedowns? Time to put the screws to them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_208"><text>Oh, speaking of business! I've got a bottle stashed, so there is business after all.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_209"><text>Got any grub? I'm hungry, need to find something to eat.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_210"><text>I'm leaving this place, I'm sick of all of it. Sure, in a crowd some things are better, but being alone isn't bad either - nobody knows anything, nobody says too much, no need to split the take. And in general, you're your own boss and master.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_211"><text>And who told me the Zone was the Klondike?! If I could find that bastard now, I'd shove his face into the shithole he sent me into.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_212"><text>Listen, pal, don't go sniffing around too much here. Who, what, where... some smartass you are...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_213"><text>How would I know? I don't make plans for myself; whatever hand I get dealt, that's how it'll be.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_214"><text>It's time to get moving on a job, instead of sitting here... grown into one spot. Soon you won't get anyone to lift his ass at all.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_215"><text>Why are you buzzing around here asking questions? Are you a prosecutor or something, that I have to answer you?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_216"><text>I'm going to sleep. Some people sleep like the dead, and I'm supposed to stand guard over them. All of you can go to hell, I'm sick of it!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_217"><text>We brought down one hell of a boar! We'll feast, drink, make merry, and snack on boar meat. Drop by the fire.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_218"><text>Those ex-cops don't understand a damn thing - I mean the Duty grunts. They should sit in the Bar and keep out of here, but no - they keep pushing in, dumb as zombies. We'll smack them in the teeth again if they show up, then again, and then some.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_219"><text>Tomorrow it's our shift to rot at the checkpoint. Damn, I really don't want to, but I'll have to.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_220"><text>Lukash keeps saying we shouldn't waste ammo. And he says we should drink less, too. Well, ammo I understand, but why limit yourself on drinking? We've been dry for two whole days already. Right now we'll wet that dry spell.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_221"><text>The senior tells me, go recruit stalkers to our side, he says, because Duty is recruiting them and we need to lure them over. Like I've got nothing better to do, sure, I'm racing off... They'll come by themselves. No normal guy will stay in Duty for long. They'll all crawl over to us, no recruiting needed.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_222"><text>There's a job nearby, just need to wait for night...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_223"><text>We stashed a crate of vodka somewhere recently. Now nobody remembers where. We couldn't have drunk the whole crate back then... though those mugs could drain a crate in one evening. Need to search properly.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_224"><text>I'm thinking: to drink or not to drink? On one hand, a drink wouldn't hurt. On the other, I absolutely can't today... but I want to. So I'm thinking.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_225"><text>I'll take more food, booze, ammo, and get the hell out of here, somewhere quiet. I'm sick of everything. I can't look at these drunk and stoned faces anymore.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_226"><text>I'm thinking who'd be best to hand the artifacts over to. One stalker here set me up with them. Maybe quietly run to the Cordon? The Bar's dangerous, somebody might find out.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_227"><text>Today or tomorrow we'll go drop some bloodsuckers. They've bred again... Where do they even come from?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_228"><text>I'm going to shoot cats. They make fine mittens and hats. Dogs make good fur boots, too. It's not winter now, sure, but as they say: "prepare your sled in summer".</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_229"><text>Same as usual. We'll shoot wildlife, what else...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_230"><text>We'll rest, then go beyond the bridge and hunt there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_231"><text>The guys are planning to go to Туманная чаща [TERM?]. I don't know why drag myself there when there's plenty of game right here...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_232"><text>Our boys want to go after a bloodsucker. They say they saw one in Чаща [TERM?]. I'm not going, to hell with that... A Bloodsucker isn't a Boar or a Flesh.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_233"><text>We'll sit, rest, get some food in us... In short, we're not going anywhere today, and tomorrow we'll see.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_234"><text>Forget your business... it can wait. Sit down, have a drink, grab a bite, and tomorrow come hunting with us.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_235"><text>I'm thinking of weaving a net for tushkanos. They're stupid, they run in a whole pack at once, so we could take them all in one go... Just need to find some rope.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_236"><text>Why so curious? I need to visit the bushes. Coming with me? We'll squat side by side and have a nice little chat...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_237"><text>I'm going to Agroprom. Some buddy there is offering a good assault rifle. Costs a whole crate of vodka! Greedy bastard...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_238"><text>I need to find some powder, laundry powder... You can find anything here if you want - cocaine, heroin, even LSD... Any kind you like. But laundry powder? You can't find it in broad daylight with a lantern.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_239"><text>I've got huge plans. I'm going to find loot so good that all at once - bang! And you're a millionaire. Then bam! - exchanged the money, snap! - and you're in the Canaries...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_240"><text>There's a rumor that the Agroprom underground is packed with goods beyond counting. They crawl in there practically in their underwear with a slingshot, and come out in exoskeletons, loaded with loot, with three assault rifles hanging from each neck. I want to touch that... fairy tale too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_241"><text>I was told some oddball in Dark Valley buys tushkano heads. I beat down a ridiculous pile of them! But I never figured out who's buying, so I need to go look, because they've started stinking...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_242"><text>There's this angle - I'm thinking of taking a run to Sultan... Know him? Hey, buddy, you don't know a damn thing! He's the real deal. If you need to score a gun that shoots where it needs to all by itself, look for Sultan, and you'll be happy! And he splits everything fair with the guys. Not like this one... Only Султаныч [TERM?] charges serious money, but it's worth it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_243"><text>Need to get my teeth fixed. Haven't slept for two days, my whole face is swollen. Need to find a doctor. Know where?</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_244"><text>I picked up a good artifact in one place and thought: here it is, happiness, ha!..
I ordered a serious suit, they tell me the order's ready, come pick it up. I signal that I'll grab it now, run to the stash for the artifact, stick my nose into the container, and there's a pile of some kind of shit! Now I don't even know what to do...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_245"><text>Bought some sausage from some bastard, now my belly's killing me. Looking for pills, searched every medkit the boys have - everything is there, but no loperamide or anything like it. Crawling from bush to bush and eating charcoal from campfires. Misery.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_246"><text>Barkeep asked me to find some guy, said he owed him. So I'm looking, he promised to make it worth my while...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_247"><text>I want out of here! My hair's coming out in clumps, my ribs have been broken three times. Dogs bit me too, maybe it got infected - won't heal at all... To hell with all this extreme shit!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_248"><text>There he goes, sniffing around... There was one curious, talkative type here, and by morning there was no loot and no gun, the little bastard had been casing it all and swiped it. Move along, man. I don't know you and you don't know me. Don't make me do something we'll both regret!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_249"><text>You're simple as a penny, man! Walked up and started trying to be friends right away... You're a stranger, sorry, but I'm not going anywhere with you.</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_250"><text>Need to go gather some broken crates; firewood's running out. If you poke around here, there are boxes all over... By the way, where do they come from, do you know? Have you heard about the death trucks yet? Ah, right... sorry. Anyway, I think those trucks carry more than just corpses; they haul junk too, crates, empty containers, maybe not so empty... So when you suddenly find a pile of crates, it's clear a truck passed through recently. Only one problem: where do the trucks themselves go afterward...</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_251"><text>Why are you asking so much? You'd be better off doing something useful yourself: haul over a couple of empty boxes for firewood - look how many they've dragged in again. Rookies come in and haul whole chests with them like hamsters, one dragging a wooden box, another a metal one. They think they'll immediately find a heap of artifacts here, pack the box full, and adieu. Sure, keep dreaming!</text></string>
<string id="dm_action_info_252"><text>Heard a chopper flew over somewhere again? Seems they're carrying some kind of cargo, but where, for whom? And where do they land in the Zone? I think they don't land at all; they drop different crates from above, and people haul them off later... But who sponsors all of it is impossible to understand... Means somebody benefits from keeping people here and feeding them at least like this. Nothing but riddles in this Zone...</text></string>

<string id="dm_strelok_info_0"><text>Get lost, will you? What kind of crap are you spouting?</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_1"><text>What shooter... We're all shooters here... Well, every other man, maybe...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_2"><text>Strelok? Who's that supposed to be? Hm... Haven't heard anything.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_3"><text>Uh... Is that some kind of nickname? I don't remember, I don't think there was anything like that.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_4"><text>A shooter or a stalker? I didn't quite hear... Which stalker, be specific! Ah, Strelok... No, haven't heard of him.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_5"><text>Strelok... Strelok... Something's rattling around in my head, like someone told me. Damn, can't remember!</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_6"><text>Of course I've heard. Don't you know? He was one of the first to load up with loot here and slip out of the Zone. Now he's probably got a villa in the Canaries. What else? I'd have done the same... Ah, if I had loot like his, but you probably won't find that kind anymore.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_7"><text>Are you asking about that Strelok, the one they say made it to the center? Yeah, there's a story like that, but I don't really buy it, though who knows... there are rumors about the center, so somebody must have been there, why not Strelok. But honestly, I don't care.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_8"><text>Strelok, you say... Heard something about him, only it all seems like bullshit to me. Like he reached the center and all that. All kinds of stories about him go around, but it all smells like folklore... or fairy tales, like Мюнхгаузен [TERM?].</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_9"><text>Why don't you ask about Семецкий [TERM?] too, and I'll tell you where he was and where he died... They're myths of the Zone, isn't that clear? Don't fall for all that crap... People say all kinds of things about Семецкий [TERM?] or that same Strelok.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_10"><text>Heard of him. They say he was a tough stalker. I don't even know how long you have to live in the Zone to grow into it like Strelok did... A legend, that's the word. And where is he now?..</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_11"><text>They say all kinds of things... I don't believe all of it, of course, but on the other hand, why not. Say, the Wild West once had its own legends and hard men too... Everyone knew them, and those people really existed. So why couldn't there be one here... I don't know, anyway.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_12"><text>Strelok? Yeah... definitely a legend... I mean, a real hard man, not just some nobody like you and me. All right, don't take offense... really, people say a lot about Strelok, whether it's all worth believing is another question. But if they talk, that means such a man definitely existed, or exists, or maybe he's some kind of collective image... A mystery, in a word.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_13"><text>Heard they say he made it all the way to the center of the Zone. They're probably lying about that, because if he reached the center, everyone would have charged into the center already, since the route was known. I figure Strelok is something like Чёрный Сталкер [TERM?] or whatever, just stalker tales, you know, local fairy stories. Though who knows, maybe somebody really did get somewhere.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_14"><text>Sure I've heard. Heard he was making his way to the center of the Zone... Whether he made it or not, I don't know. Those stories about him were interesting for a while, I don't even remember now. Truth is, most of them were jokes like about Штирлиц [TERM?] or Чапаев [TERM?]... But think for yourself: if a man hadn't done something out of the ordinary, nobody would tell stories about him at all...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_15"><text>Yeah, Strelok is definitely a legend... no less. Could you handle five Chimeras and a Controller alone, all at once? He could. Well, maybe they exaggerate a bit, but still, imagine how tough you'd have to be, even if they added a couple of Chimeras...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_16"><text>I think he's a very unusual stalker, but it's not even about him. Fine, say he reached the center of the Zone, fine, handled monsters with one hand tied behind his back, but tell me, how did anyone else learn about it? Everyone couldn't have made up the same stories at once, and I've heard plenty, I won't repeat all that nonsense to you... I'm just personally curious who went with him and told it all in such detail, huh? All right, forget it...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_17"><text>I heard people in the Bar talking about him, saying he stocked up completely to go to the center of the Zone. They even say he was looking for partners, but people weren't too eager to hire on with his team... You never know; he goes God knows where, he might crawl out himself, but his partner? There... people didn't trust him much. Haven't heard talk about him for a long time; you're probably the first to ask lately. I don't even know what to answer...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_18"><text>They said this Strelok wasn't a stalker at all, but some kind of spec-ops type. I'm telling you straight! I heard he took down a squad of mercenaries without breaking a sweat. Well? What, you don't think he's special forces?</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_19"><text>I don't know whether they were talking about Strelok or not, but something like that is on the tip of my tongue... Like one tough guy laid out almost the whole Agroprom, soldiers and all... Probably bullshit, but since you asked, that's what came to mind.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_20"><text>Strelok, I'll tell you, was a born stalker... meaning he still exists somewhere, I think. I didn't know him, but I was told he could bring back things that would make your mother weep, wherever the hell you could even find them! Things like he brought back, nobody anywhere ever found. That's how it was...</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_21"><text>Yeah, heard of him. But I'll tell you this: I don't like him much. There's something seriously suspicious about him. Judge for yourself: walks around the Zone like it's his own home, brings back unbelievable loot... and in general... I don't like it. Better don't bring him up again.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_22"><text>I heard... just between us, of course, that Diodor somehow put a charm on him. Because whenever he comes back from a run, he disappears somewhere. And note, Diodor disappears too. Then both come back, he unloads the loot, and the Bar parties for a week... Something's off here.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_23"><text>Strelok is a stalker, I'll tell you... well, a stalker not like you and me. I didn't know him personally, but I knew one man who went on a run with him. So in that run he ended up completely naked - I mean an anomaly ate his gear, but he managed to crawl out. Strelok helped him - gave him some supplies, patched him up. Saved him, in short... So I'd go on a run with Strelok without question.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_24"><text>Yeah... He was a stalker, not like today's rookies. He used to go alone... no, can you imagine, alone, into the bloodsucker village. Could you do that? Well, if you made it through alone, I'd definitely think you were Strelok... ha... All right, don't twitch, nobody else can do that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_25"><text>He was a born stalker. I didn't know him, but people told me... Said he went to Radar alone... Just between us, I don't believe it, but an authoritative stalker said it, so I nodded along. Personally, I think it's impossible - alone through Radar.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_26"><text>I heard he worked with someone. Well, I didn't hear it myself, but one guy told me someone told him that he had a whole crew. And they split whatever loot they found, but that one thing they didn't split, and after that Strelok disappeared... That's what I heard.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_27"><text>Yeah, I think it's all crap. Sure, someone distinguished himself somewhere, so what? Of course rumors start, and gossip piles on. Don't stuff your head with it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_28"><text>You asked about Strelok, and I'll tell you this: anyone who stands out in the Zone is already a legend. Yeah. Because if you're a fool, you'll die as soon as things get tight, and if you survive, you're already a legend... Probably same with Strelok. So he had some rough scrape somewhere and survived; why yell "legend" across the whole Zone now...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_29"><text>Buddy, forget those stories, that's my advice. People say all kinds of things; if you listen and try to measure up to hardcases like that, I'm telling you straight - you won't last a month. In the Zone you don't need to be a legend, more like a wise little minnow... It helps you survive.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_30"><text>Don't remember anyone like that... Remind me what was so special he did, then I'll tell you... Well, if not, then not.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_31"><text>Is he the one who was filling everyone's ears in the Bar about how he made it to the center of the Zone? Or are you asking about someone else? I didn't quite get it...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_32"><text>Who? You believe that kind of crap? I can make up as many stories as you want about how I kissed the Monolith or made a wish... In short, forget it!</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_33"><text>What Strelok? What kind of handle is that? Never heard it.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_34"><text>Is that some kind of nickname? I don't remember, don't think there was anything like that.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_35"><text>Who he is, I don't know. If he were some authority, everyone would know, but nobody's heard of him.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_36"><text>Strelok... Something's rattling around in my head, can't remember.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_37"><text>Whose crew is he from? What kind of boys does he run with? Find that out, then ask. We don't have any like that here...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_38"><text>Is that the one who filled everyone's ears about how he reached the center of the Zone? I could spin you a million fairy tales like that...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_39"><text>Who? What, is he supposed to be tough enough that everyone should know him? I don't know any authority like that.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_40"><text>Are you looking for Жека-Стрелок [TERM?]? You won't find him - dogs are already finishing off his bones; he flew into an anomaly drunk. Idiot.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_41"><text>One buddy told me about some Strelok, I think... Don't remember exactly what; we were drinking then, but something interesting about him, like he hit a decent jackpot.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_42"><text>It's all bullshit... pure chatter... There is no Strelok and never was anyone with a handle like that.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_43"><text>You people and this Strelok. Someone already asked before you... Looks like this Strelok screwed him hard, so he was looking for him... obvious what for.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_44"><text>Forget it! You won't find him. Looking for someone by name in the Zone is a dead end. Maybe he's already changed ten nicknames and twenty places.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_45"><text>Haven't heard of him... What do you need him for? Did he rip you off or what? That's your business, but there's nobody like that here...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_46"><text>Heard something about someone like that. They say he's some kind of badass. Only he hasn't been here, otherwise everyone would know.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_47"><text>Is he one of the stalkers or what? I don't know, maybe we've seen him, but our boys don't ask their names - frisk them and let them pass... Asking every stalker his name is too much honor.</text></string> 
<string id="dm_strelok_info_48"><text>There was some talk in the Bar about Strelok, I think. I gathered people didn't trust him much - too quick and nimble for the Zone. Here one moment, there the next...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_49"><text>I meet him every day! Matter of fact, there he goes. Sick of him bumming cigarettes; he refuses to smoke his own on principle, says they're all a special brand - "shooter smokes".</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_50"><text>You can't count all the shooters around here! One fires, another blasts away...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_51"><text>I haven't heard anything about you either, and you're asking me about some Strelok...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_52"><text>Wait, wait... Recently some boys were walking somewhere from the Garbage, then three more rolled up to them... There was one with a bald spot, he shot clean, from one knee, bang-bang! Boar down in two shots - legs up, dog in one - face in the dirt, smack... I'm telling you straight! And his crew called him a shooter, that happened. Only they all left somewhere right away...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_53"><text>There was one here... a sniper. Always carried a little notebook. Went after artifacts and marked the route in it, kept writing things down. Shot excellently - on a bet, they say, he put a hole through a coin from fifty meters with a PM. Yeah, sure, he was one hell of a shooter... Then boars trampled him on the Garbage, buried long ago.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_54"><text>Who? Strelok, Strelok... Ah! The one who stole a suit from Ваня Варежка [TERM?]? Put it on and ran off somewhere. Did he swipe something from you too, is that why you're looking for him? Not the one? Well, I don't know then...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_55"><text>I knew one shooter. A real cowboy. Fired pistols with both hands, showing off. Showed off so much the bloodsuckers ate him, only his slippers were left.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_56"><text>Someone by the campfire was saying there's a little crew of guys who rummage where even a snork is afraid to stick its snout. Strelok was supposedly their ringleader. So he led them all straight to the next world... They got wiped out somewhere at Yantar... Only rumors are left of them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_57"><text>I know him! A month ago he borrowed a pack of 5.45 rounds from me. Just for a week, the damn swindler... If I meet him, I'll kill him! If you see him anywhere, whistle for me too.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_58"><text>Who is that? Not the one who recently handed some "Бабкины бусы [TERM?]" to Barkeep in the Bar? Know that artifact? Right, me neither. And he found it. Where, he didn't say... Took a fat haul for it, and that's understandable, if it really is an artifact, things like that don't lie under every bush. Lucky bastard!</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_59"><text>Strelok? I've not only heard of him, I've seen him. He's sitting in the Swamps right now, look for him there.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_60"><text>He's that red-haired one, built like a wardrobe. Interesting tattoo he's got, right? A church with domes... He's probably in Dark Valley now...</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_61"><text>There was an old guy like that; Voronin wanted to bring him and his group under his thumb, so Duty members killed the lot of them.</text></string>
<string id="dm_strelok_info_62"><text>He already left the Zone. He and the mercenaries stole some secret chemical reconnaissance vehicle from the military and took off.</text></string>
</string_table>